<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The obligation of human laws discussed. By J.H.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224178</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834537</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834537</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39038</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39038)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1812:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The obligation of human laws discussed. By J.H.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 142, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year,</date>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.H. = John Humfrey.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Philosophy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion and law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39038:1"/>
            <p>THE OBLIGATION Of Human LAWS Diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>We are to give to Princes and the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that are ſet over us by God, ſuch Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and obedience as may not hurt us. <hi>Polycarpus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Too rigorous were it that the breach of every Law ſhould be held a deadly ſin, a mean there is between theſe extremities, if ſo be we could find it out. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year. 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39038:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39038:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Papers were prepared againſt <hi>Eaſter</hi> Term laſt year, but the Printers failed us. Nevertheleſs the Subject being of perpetual occaſion, and ſo long as there is any Common-Wealth and Laws there is none can ſay, <hi>I have need of thee,</hi> I ſee no reaſon to hinder the coming out now to the ſame publick advantage.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Author.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:39038:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have peruſed this Diſcourſe and do judge it will be of ſingular uſe unto all ſuch as deſire conſcienti-ouſly to order their obedience unto Magiſtrates in civil things: For although it is written in the way of a defence of what was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more breifly offered unto the ſame purpoſe, yet the ſubject matter of it is ſo managed, and the truth aſſerted in it ſo vindicated from the oppoſition of another, that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Reader, will be ſatiſfied in the proper Rule of civil things, and in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of every Man making a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their own actions in reference there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. O.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39038:3"/>
            <head>THE Obligation of human Laws diſcuſſed.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I.</head>
               <p>WE have before us a famous queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is not only of great moment, conſtant uſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, but of ſo much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and doubtful diſpute, as that ſome learn'd men of great note in the Romiſh Church, have judged it fit only for the Pope in <hi>Cathedra</hi> to determine it. I am not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht ſo much as with my own books, which are from me, and much leſs with ſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as it would require to inform my ſelf,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39038:4"/>or my Readers, in the ſeveral judgements, of all, or the cheif Doctors in the Schools, with other Divines, and Lawyers, who have written of this point. But this I take to be notorious, that there are many of very great magnitude in the Church or Schools, with multitudes of ſeveral ſorts of Divines, who have, or do hold, that humane Laws bind not the Conſcience, whereof God only is the Lord, and which can be bound be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his authority, as will be confeſſed. On the contrary there be others and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of no leſs, or of greater eminence and number, who yet on both ſides, when they oppoſe one another may not defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from extremity, but that there is a <hi>mean</hi> according to the judgement of ſober and indifferent men, to be ſought in theſe things, if we can light of it.</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs I ſhould very hardly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any thing but confuſion in my own thoughts if I truſted my ſelf altogether to books, among ſuch variety. By the little I ſometimes read concerning this diſpute I muſt need ſay, it did but ſerve to leave me at a loſs, and how I have ſince retired my thoughts more into my own mind, to look upon that writing which is congenial with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39038:4"/>us, even thoſe principles of truth which nature and ſo God hath implanted in mans own heart, and having propoſed from the reſult of all a determination ſo plain, and in the middle path, being careful that neither conſcience ſhould be left looſe and diſſolute, nor tyed by Mans command or Laws, any farther then God doth tye it, It hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the reverend Author of the <hi>friendly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</hi> by an oppoſition in a <hi>Poſt-ſcript</hi> to his <hi>Appendix</hi> to draw me out to my defence, and a farther explication, mainly of what I have in a leſſer room before written.</p>
               <p>I perceive there is an expreſſion fell from me among others of reſpect, concerning the <hi>Debater,</hi> that hath moved him to ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation that I know not how I ſhall pacific him, for a man ſhall not lightly ſee two or three ſheets of paper written thus tetrically upon ſo ſmall an occaſion. <hi>I receiv'd a caſe from you, a very weighty one it is, and as weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſolidly reſolved, if the caſuiſt may be his own Judge.</hi> So he goes on; I muſt confeſs I lookt on this perſon as a Man of a moſt modeſt, humble, pious, ingenuous, calm tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and I have the ſame opinion as to his worth and abilities as I had, but I do not like the ſpirit of this <hi>appendix,</hi> there is in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſt</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:39038:5"/>ſo much gentleneſs and care of offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as hath ſeemed too much. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, here is in theſe papers ſuch a deal of animoſity, indignation, and that indeed which in women we call vixeniſh humour, but eſpecially ſuch an inveterate eſpouſing of a party, with that diſdain and contempt of every man, and thing, that appears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf, or cauſe, that there is no <hi>do</hi> with him. Nevertheleſs I muſt needs ſay for my own part I am not yet converted to his opinion, but that I muſt think ſtill that a <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> who hath not taken the <hi>Oxford</hi> Oath, may live within five miles of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration and yet be <hi>a good Chriſtian, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what is the ground for ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent expreſſion as this was, and that he ſhould continue the juſtification of it? The ground of all doth lye on this <hi>ſingle point</hi> as himſelf has it, <hi>whether humane Laws bind the conſcience?</hi> In the reſolving which point he is come here to an acknowledgement that there is <hi>difficulty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that finds none</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>may well ſuſpect that he does not fully underſtand it.</hi> And why is he ſo angry then, when he laid down his matter ſo inconſiderately in his firſt book;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39038:5"/>without any diſtinction or proviſion for any, that I ſhould ſay only he was not ſo <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flective</hi> as he ought, upon all the things at leaſt, as he was to look to in ſo great an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking? Alas, that there ſhould be ſo much vanity and elation of mind, in impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent man, that if you commend him never ſo much, for what is worthy in him, you muſt give him more then he deſerves, or he will accompt what is due, but a diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to him.</p>
               <p>If you will praiſe a Man for his valour, and ſay he is as valiant as <hi>Hector,</hi> or <hi>Judas Macca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus,</hi> it will not ſerve, unleſs you ſay alſo he exceeds <hi>Hercules,</hi> and make him wiſer too withall, then <hi>Solomon,</hi> and all Kings. <hi>I could be contented, to have wanted his good word</hi> (ſays he) <hi>upon condition he had not ſaid</hi>—What? why ſomething that is innocently true, he names, but that which ſticks, is, that I count him one more <hi>happy</hi> in his <hi>expreſſion</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abilities then in his <hi>depth</hi> or <hi>reflectiveneſs</hi> on the things he offers.</p>
               <p>Whether I have herein judged amiſs, or not, I will be content to come to ſome tryal with him, and that I may treat with this <hi>Poſt-ſcript</hi> in ſome method, it is convenient I ſhould in the firſt place propoſe the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39038:6"/>of this caſe, or queſtion, as I have tendred it together with his conception, underſtanding or apprehenſion of it. In the <hi>next</hi> place that I ſhould take notice of his objections againſt it. It is convenient then that I and he take a review of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination which he hath propoſed in the place of it. And laſtly that I anſwer to his exceptions, either here and there occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally as they fall in upon me, or more fully and induſtriouſly, at the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:39038:6"/>
               <head>CAP. II.</head>
               <p>FOr the foremoſt, I wonder the leſs that this debater does ſhow ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful contempt of my determination, when he is poſſeſſed with ſo much prejudice, as gives him not leave to mind the very main diſtinctions I offer him in it. After he hath therefore in the enſuing, firſt three leaves fallen upon a paſſage of providence, which I have ſet down as proper and indeed pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the matter of the Caſe, he enters the Liſt with theſe words. <hi>This is ſufficient to ſhow what may be expected from this new un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker, who will appear I don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t not as lame in his Reaſonings as he doth in this, and prove as unfit to determine caſes of Conſcience, as to make obſervations of providence.</hi> I do not know what kind of guſt <hi>one</hi> may have of the <hi>ſame</hi> thing which pleaſes <hi>another,</hi> but it does become any inge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uous mind to think, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39038:7"/>all men are not caſt into the ſame mould, and to take heed therefore, leaſt by cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of that which the moſt of others ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, he brings his own Judgement into queſtion, and becomes the leſs regarded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for it. And really if the ſpleen and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy, of five ſides and a half, and no leſs of about twenty leaves in all, to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe but abuſe of his paper, do not ſhew more what may be expected in this <hi>ſtale</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker, who hath come out now this fourth time to <hi>debate;</hi> then that obſervation of mine will diſcover in me, I am miſtaken. For my part let the determination of the caſe be found as ſolid as that obſervation upon the matter of it is pertinent, and I ſhall have no cauſe to be moved by his cenſure. But what is that which hath <hi>moved him</hi> thus? why, <hi>he makes me</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſuch a pittiſul Gamester that</hi> I <hi>am not reflective</hi> (here he quotes the Page wherein I have delivered that hainous word) <hi>upon more removes then one of thoſe many I ought to ſee.— Yet I have done my endeavour to comprehend him and to fathome the bottom of his deep diſcourſe.</hi> I muſt confeſs I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt my ſelf in theſe words he quotes, I ſpeak verily according to my thoughts, and I can't help that. But one would think by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39038:7"/>theſe words, we ſhould have at leaſt ſo much integrity now from this perſon, as to ſet down my determination at leaſt in my own words, being ſo few, if not made better by his, that the Reader might judge whether he does indeed look to the bottom of what I have offered, and if after theſe words he yet does not, he may be aſhamed, to expreſs himſelf thus, and ſhew ſuch a ſpirit as this is.</p>
               <p>Well in my <hi>caſe,</hi> I diſtinguiſh then firſt, between the authority of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and of his Laws and Commands. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there is a diſtinction which Dr. <hi>Field</hi> has, parallell with it, to wit, between <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> and <hi>obedience,</hi> ſubjection is that which is due or proper to the Magiſtrate, or to the authority reſiding in his perſon: Obedience is that which is due to his commands, or to the authority of his Laws. By ſubjection we are to underſtand all that which ſtands in oppoſition to reſiſtance, and ſo <hi>ſubjection</hi> in one verſe in the Apoſtle, is aequivalent with <hi>not reſiſting</hi> in the other; and the word in the Original does kindly ſerve this purpoſe. Now <hi>ſubjection</hi> being what is oppoſite to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,</hi> and what is due to the Authority which reſides in the Magiſtrates perſon, it is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39038:8"/>what is; and muſt be always due; ſo that we muſt never reſiſt, but be ſubject, becauſe this authority always reſides there. But obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which is proper to his Laws, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, is not due always, becauſe there may be ſome Laws, or things, commanded, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void of Gods authority, and then if we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them not, we do not ſin. This is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, or very near it, in two caſes, by this perſon; in a caſe of ſin, and in a caſe of intollerable grievance, from whence others will follow.</p>
               <p>The other diſtinction is between the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the <hi>conſcience,</hi> and of the outward Man. Let this learned perſon now take of his eyes from the paper, and conſider but a while before he reads on, what he thinks I mean by, and to what uſe I put this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and he may take the beſt conjecture whether he be not ſhort in his <hi>comprehenſion</hi> of it. The <hi>outward Man</hi> let us know then is obliged by the penalty, the ſword, or wrath: and by Gods command not to reſiſt, or to be <hi>ſubject</hi> in reference to his authority re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in the Magiſtrate himſelf. There are two things then you ſee go to the binding the outward Man, Gods command of not reſiſting, or being ſubject to the Powers,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39038:8"/>and the Magiſtrates ſword, and force. If we muſt never or by no means reſiſt, then the Magiſtrate may make us do what he will, or elſe we muſt ſuffer. We cannot avoid ſuffering but by reſiſting or obeying, Reſiſt we never may, obey we muſt then, if we will not ſuffer, unleſs the caſe be in the matter of ſin, wherein we all agree in one, that we muſt always ſuffer. The <hi>Conſcience</hi> is obliged only by Gods <hi>will,</hi> which is the adequate Rule of Conſcience. I will explain it farther. There is Gods will, and Mans will, a divine and humane Obligation. When God will have a thing to be done as well as Man, I do accompt the Conſcience is bound, becauſe the Obligation is divine: but when Man will have it done, and God requires it not, but only his will is that whatſoever be impoſed, the ſubject how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever muſt not rebel, I do account the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to the thing to be humane altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the outward Man bound only. <hi>Jus Regis vocatur</hi> (ſayes <hi>Grotius</hi> I remember ſomewhere) <hi>non quia Rex ita agens juſte ageret ſed quia it a agenti nemini liceret vim ullam opponere.</hi> That is as much as to ſay there is a double right a Magiſtrate hath in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands or actions; A <hi>moral</hi> right when he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39038:9"/>
                  <hi>commands,</hi> or <hi>does,</hi> thoſe things which he ought to do, or command: or a <hi>Political</hi> right, (called by <hi>Samuel</hi> the <hi>manner of the King</hi>) when though he commands or does thoſe things he ought not (or what God does not allow, but he is accountable to him for them,) yet the ſubject may not reſiſt him in thoſe commands, or acts, and deliver himſelf from them by force. When the Magiſtrate uſes the firſt of theſe Rights, I account the conſcience is obliged: when the ſecond the outward man onely. The termes are uſed we know by grave Divines ſuch as Biſhop <hi>Downham</hi> (to name no other) in his tract of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty:</hi> and it will be one benefit of theſe papers, if we can retain with good diſcretion, and ſenſe, what is ſo uſefull, as rather then be without, we ſhall ſtill uſe though with none. And by this diſtinction it does appear, how all that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which hitherto this man hath fancyed conſequent to my determination, does fall away as the leaves from the trees in ſummer. For ſo long as we do all acknowledge the authority of the preſent Magiſtrate in his perſon with our ſubjection thereunto, that in no caſe it is lawfull to <hi>reſiſt,</hi> whereby the outward man comes to be bound, ſo that if
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39038:9"/>he will, and when he will, he can force it to obey by his ſword, there is not ſo much as any certain diſobedience, and much leſs is there any danger to his Government, through Inſurrection, or Rebellion, that follows from my opinion.</p>
               <p>If in Religious things, or moral, when the Magiſtrate commands any thing againſt a mans conſcience, and the Subject does not obey, his authority nevertheleſs is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, though he cannot force them in that caſe to obedience if he would: how ſhall we think but in things which are ſecular, where be can force them to obey if he will, that there is any danger to his Government, for their obeying ſuch and ſuch a Law on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe they dare not to reſiſt (I mean for Gods ſake that they dare not) and not out of conſcience elſe? I would have this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and intelligent, but at this time over engaged perſon, who <hi>yet</hi> ſees not all the <hi>removes</hi> which are to be ſeen in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for all his anger at me for my thinking ſo, to conſider whether there be not many learned Men, Writers and others, who hold that the Laws of Men do not obleige the Conſcience at all; and that they cannot, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conſcience is Gods Throne, but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39038:10"/>man only<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and does he think that all ſuch muſt be ſo ſhallow that they are not able to avoid his extemporanous conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or that they ſee not the weakneſs of ſuch a <hi>Gameſter</hi> (ſeeing he calls himſelf ſo, for it was not I uſed that word) who hath not come yet ſo far here, as to conſideration with himſelf? For I ſay, is there any Men of parts or learning thinks he, that fear God and are Chriſtians, who hold it lawful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, or to deſtroy all Society and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> And if not, how comes it to paſs he ſhould not reſolve with himſelf, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if ſuch conſequences which he would faſten on me will be avoided and denyed by thoſe that hold that human Laws do never bind the Conſcience, they may and muſt be denyed by me with more facility, who have determined that human Laws do with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction bind it, but not <hi>indefinitely</hi> as he does.</p>
               <p>And what is that diſtinction then which after theſe two other not comprehended by the <hi>Debater,</hi> does determine the queſtion in hand? That we are to be always ſubject as to the Authority of the Magiſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf I have ſaid and yet that we are not bound always to obey his commands, that is, we are not bound always in Conſcience, when
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39038:10"/>yet we are bound in the outward Man. This being ſaid, the determining diſtinction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Laws or Commands, which do bind, and which do not bind the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is this. The commands of the Magiſtrate are either ſuch as are agreeable to Gods will, or not agreeable to his will. Thoſe that are, bind it: Thoſe that are not, bind it not. The Reaſon is, becauſe the authority the Magiſtrate hath to command, is derived from, and to be founded in Gods will. In the way, <hi>The Caſuiſt</hi> (ſayes this benign Debater) <hi>ſeems to have no low op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nion of his own performance, but rather thinks we may chance to be beholding to him for a new Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Here ſayes he, is that very mean indeed for ought</hi> I <hi>know which is wanting. A great diſcovery! and for ought</hi> I <hi>know may any body reply that which is not wanting but the very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous extream into which the people are apt to run, as he is to follow thoſe with whom</hi> I <hi>have had to deal.</hi> As for thoſe with whom he hath been dealing I preſume it will be found there is nothing of this determination in what they have ſaid; if &amp; I did not eſteem it uncommon, I ſhould (I muſt confeſs) have reſtrained it.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39038:11"/>Or if I did not think it conſiderable, I ſhould have held my peace alſo. But after this ſcornfulneſs of his why did he not preſent us with that <hi>mean</hi> which follows in the words of the Caſe, that the Reader might judge, whether it be any diſcovery indeed, or none, or whether it deſerves this Mans contempt or not? For as <hi>Cato</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cicero</hi> when he played upon the <hi>Stoicks</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions (which another hath noted) <hi>Cicero</hi> makes others laugh, but is himſelf ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous: So ſay I, this perſon ſtrives here to offer me and my determination to contempt, but the things I have ſaid will bear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out, and he does but diſcover hereby his own deſert. What is that <hi>mean</hi> then which follows? The words in the Caſe are theſe. <q>That the Laws or Commands of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate (even in Political and indifferent things) does no leſs then bind the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when he is the executioner of <hi>Gods will,</hi> but though the <hi>outward man</hi> (out of the Caſe of ſin) may be bound if you will, the <hi>conſcience</hi> cannot be obleiged, and ought to be ſtill kept free, when he is the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner only of his <hi>own.</hi>
                  </q> It may be the Debater will not yet be beholding to me
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39038:11"/>for this, and he may chooſe, when perhaps others will, and take it never the leſs kindly for that. It fares with thoſe that beat their heads about notions, as it doth with Miners; they are the condemned Men, and the Gold they dig becomes others: Never the leſs the Man that hath been digging &amp; finds a Veine, may ſay, what he hath found is Gold as well as another, and without pride. He doth not commend himſelf, for his commending the Gold. I think verily that that which I I have here digged is the mean, the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den mean we are to find in this caſe, and not an <hi>extream wherein I follow any</hi> as he ſayes: but the avoiding both extreams. The one is of thoſe who hold that human Laws do not bind the Conſcience at all: and the other ſuch as hold as this Man did when he firſt unadviſedly ſet out, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will continue of the mind ſtill, that they bind indefinitely without diſcrimination, at leaſt ſo far by all means, as <hi>Dr. Manton</hi> his good Neighbor, and every one ſuch as he (whatſoever the breakers of other Laws may be) might be none of Chriſts Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or good Chriſtians on that account.</p>
               <p>Well! The will of God which deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the commands of Man to be obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39038:12"/>or not, upon the Conſcience, muſt be conſidered in the concerns of <hi>Religion:</hi> in things <hi>morall:</hi> and in things <hi>civil</hi> or Political. The rule or Law of God in things Religious, is the Scripture. The rule or Law of God in things <hi>moral</hi> is the Light of Nature, which alſo is the will of God, as the word is. The Rule and ſupream Law which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for things Political is the <hi>common good.</hi> If the Magiſtrate command any thing in <hi>Religion</hi> and it be not <hi>according</hi> to Gods word, then Conſcience cannot be bound to it as <hi>Religious,</hi> though the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man I think therein alſo is bound, if it be not againſt Gods word. It the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate command any thing of moral concern, if it be againſt the Law of nature, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principles of Light in Man, that is the moral Law in the heart, the Conſcience cannot be bound but muſt refuſe it. If he command any thing which is <hi>civil</hi> or <hi>Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> and it be againſt the common good, then is it not agreeable to Gods will, being not conſonant to the rule he hath commanded for civils, and conſequently the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot be obleiged by it upon that accompt. In the mean while ſo long as it is not againſt conſcience otherwiſe, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39038:12"/>is ſo long as it is not ſin, the <hi>outward man</hi> is bound, and if the Magiſtrate will conſtrain a perſon to it, rather then ſuffer he will obey.</p>
               <p>There are ſeveral books and Sermons of Miniſters about Religion, which do bind the Readers and Hearers by vertue of Gods will: but the ſupream Rule is Gods Word, unto which conſequently, if what they have ſaid; or writ, be not conſonant, the Conſcience is not bound, and according as the Conſcience of a Man is convinced, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which the Miniſter ſays be agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the word or not, ſo is it bound, or not bound by it. The caſe is the ſame in Laws. The Magiſtrate doth give us ſuch and ſuch particular commands, or Laws. His authority he hath from God. The will of God as the ſupream Law, or Rule, in Politicalls, is, that the common good be attended and advanced. <hi>They are Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters a ſending continually upon this very thing.</hi> So far as his Laws, or commands then are agreeable to the common good, ſo far is his Authority good, and muſt obleige the Conſcience being from God. And ſo long as a man is convinced in Conſcience,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39038:13"/>that they are agreeable thereunto, he muſt be in Conſcience obleiged: but if he be ſincerely perſwaded that ſuch or ſuch a thing commanded, be not for the publick good, the caſe is but the ſame with what I ſaid in Religion, when the Miniſters ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation diſagrees with the word. The Magiſtrate is but Gods <hi>Miniſter</hi> in Politicals, and his commands diſagreeing, with the ſupream Law, the <hi>common good,</hi> the Conſcience cannot be obleiged in this Caſe. Nevertheleſs, ſo long as the outward Man is in the Magiſtrates power, and the Subject may not reſiſt, he can command obedience, out of the caſe of ſin, when he pleaſes to exert his Sword.</p>
               <p>Before I paſs off, I am made a little ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible how apt our queſtion may be wreſted into a diſpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e about Terms. It is hardly proper to ſay this or that Law binds the Conſcience, for Conſcience is the diſcerner of my duty, and it were more proper to ſay my conſcience binds me to this Law, then that this Law binds it. It is ſcarce proper neither to ſay the Conſcience is bound, ſeeing it is the perſon is bound. Conſcience is placed in the underſtanding, and when a thing becomes a Mans duty, the <hi>will</hi> is obleiged rather then the <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:39038:13"/>It is not eaſie likewiſe to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how the outward man is bound with diſtinction to the Conſcience, conſidering that this obligation hath it's riſe, and vertue, from our duty of not <hi>reſiſting,</hi> unto which we are always bound in Conſcience. The term <hi>Reſiſting</hi> likewiſe is liable to diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of acceptation.</p>
               <p>It is convenient therefore for me, in my way to give the ſenſe of my Terms (if it be not yet done enough) to prevent needleſs contention. By human Laws I underſtand the declaration of the will of the rightful Governor, what he would have his Subjects do, I will not alſo put in the end of Laws, <hi>in order to the common good,</hi> becauſe that will preſently ſpoyl the queſtion. For where the efficient is our rightful Ruler, and the Law ſerves indeed for that end, or hath it's right final cauſe alſo, there is no queſtion of its obligation. Yet if I leave out the end the queſtion indeed may be whether ſuch a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration be a <hi>Law,</hi> rather then whether it <hi>binds.</hi> Nevertheleſs as I make a caſe of conſcience of it (and count all our Acts of Parliament Laws) it is all one in effect to me, whether you ſay, ſuch a Law binds not, or ſuch an <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> is no <hi>Law,</hi> and binds not. <hi>Ex quo intelliges eos qui pernicioſa et injuſta populis juſſa
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39038:14"/>deſcripſerius, cum contra feceriut quod polliciti pro feſſi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſlat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, quoduis potius tuliſſe quam leges. Cicero de legious.</hi> By Conſcience I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a faculty in Man of deſcerning Gods Judgement concerning himſelf and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It is more proper to ſay a faculty is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiged, then an habit, or an Act; and that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty which man hath hereunto, is charged (whilſt himſelf is) to judge whether ſuch a thing commanded be his duty in relation to God, or not. By obligation I underſtand the conſtitution of a due; <hi>Obligare eſt jus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituere.</hi> By obligation of the <hi>Conſcience</hi> I underſtand the conſtituting a thing to bedue from me ſo that if I do it not I muſt account or judge that God will condemn me for the neglect, or the making a thing my duty ſo that if I leave it undone I ſin. The obligation of the <hi>outward man</hi> I account the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a thing to be due from me ſo as if I do it not, I may not reſiſt, though I be puniſhed; or I may be puniſhed, and ought not to reſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, though I could avoid both the thing, and puniſhment by reſiſtance. The word, <hi>lacere,</hi> ſays <hi>Grotius</hi> (from one line of whom, a man ſhall have more Inſtruction ſometimes then from anothers book) is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed <hi>in id quod impune fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and in <hi>id quod v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tio caret.</hi> So muſt we ſay the word <hi>obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:39038:14"/>is diſtinguiſhed into that which if we do not the thing makes us liable to puniſhment (<hi>in foro humano,</hi> or according to the law:) or that which if we do it not makes us liable to ſin. That is, there is an obligation human only (which we have had before) that tyes us to obedience upon the penalty of the law: or an obligation divine alſo, which ties us to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon the pain of Gods diſpleaſure, &amp; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal condemnation. The one of theſe we call the obligation of the outward man, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Conſcience. By reſiſtance, laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I underſtand the repelling force with force. The word reſiſtance, may be taken <hi>largely</hi> or <hi>ſtrictly. Reſiſtitur contra Imperium agendo aut vim vi reprim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndo.</hi> I take it in the laſt and ſtrict ſence. Let me yet note one thing more, when we diſtinguiſh in the obligation of human laws, between the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man</hi> and the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> we do not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the outward man from the <hi>will,</hi> when we diſtinguiſh it from the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> The <hi>will</hi> is wrought upon under both obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, through fear of mans law, and through fear of Gods. If you divide the outward man from the <hi>will,</hi> you cannot bind it, but <hi>Phyſically,</hi> by putting it in Bonds and Fetters. But the obleiging it by the <hi>will,</hi> is binding it with an human obligation;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39038:15"/>and that I account too, is not morally, but <hi>politicaly</hi> (as I have intimated,) to wit as human laws are, <hi>norma humani judicij,</hi> the man who breaketh a bad law, is according to that law to be adjudged to its penalty, <hi>and in ſenſu politico humano</hi> is an offendor of the law ſo that if he be puniſhed by the judge, who judgeth by that law, he muſt ſubmit, yet ſeeing the Law is no other then ſuch, he is not made a <hi>ſinner</hi> by that breach, or to be condemned by God. To ſum up my opinion then without the terms, that thoſe that will may aſſaile me fairly in my ſence I am perſwaded as Gods <hi>will</hi> is not mans, ſo every command of man in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things is not the command of God: but that when there is no declaration of the magiſtrates will, but it does make the thing he would have, to be due from us ſo, as he may puniſh us by his law for the not doing if he pleaſe, and we muſt bear it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out defending our ſelves by force, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently he may compell us to any thing not ſinful by that means: yet does not every declaration of his will, make the thing he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires to be our duty, ſo, that we are neceſſarily guilty of ſin, if it be not done; but contraily though many a man lives and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39038:15"/>dyes in the breach of ſome laws and ſtatutes of the realm (ſo long as they offer no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to the Ruler, nor ſcandal to their brethren, nor reſiſt if they be brought to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer) they may be <hi>good Chriſtians</hi> for all that (to come to our firſt lock which our debater) and <hi>ſervants of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I have no more that I know needfull to be ſupplyed, but onely to do this: to produce what I have in my Caſe it ſelf, that the main notion I offer here, and there may appear to be the ſame: and to vindicate that authority which alone ſufficed me then, and ſhall now, for my confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The words which I offer in my Caſe are theſe. <hi>Power</hi> (ſay I) <hi>is a right to rule or command. This right in the nature of the thing muſt ariſe from the grant or will of the ſupream Lord, which is God; without whoſe will (or that grant or Charter which is an act of his will) no power can be derived to any. Now that grant or will of God which conſtitutes any to rule, or to be his Miniſter, being for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good, (He is the Miniſter of God for our good ſayes the text) it muſt follow that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not indeed for the peoples good, the Magiſtrate is not to command, becauſe it is Gods will that he commands only for their good.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39038:16"/>And it he do command any matter that is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that command hath no authority as to the Conſcience at all as being without the warrant of Gods will.</hi> I know I have ſet down this in a few lines, but it hath been the fruit of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall thoughts and years. I thought good to confirm it with one teſtimony of Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> and I perceive this debater ſeems offended, and to accuſe me of diſingenuity for it, as if I had done him wrong. It is neceſſary therefore that I turn again to that Dr. and ſee; only I muſt ſay that I am glad (I muſt confeſs) that I have here ſuch an authority as this Dr. ſo full for me, nevertheleſs Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> is not (as farr as I know in a tittle) the <hi>author</hi> to me; but a <hi>witneſs</hi> to the light I offer. In the third Book of his Caſes, and the firſt chapter, he comes to treat of human laws, and what obligation they paſs on the Conſcience. In his firſt rule he tells us, the Conſcience is obleiged directly and actively to obey the Laws of Man. Several learned Authors, together with Nine Arguments to the contrary, are propoſed, which he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving very hardly aſſayled, comes to his next Rule, that human Laws bind not when there is any intollerable, or grievous evil in the obedience. To make out this, be proceeds
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39038:16"/>to a third Rule, that the Laws of our ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, that are not juſt and good, do not obleige the Conſcience, and then ſhewing what Laws are ſuch he tells us, that a Law is unjuſt that contributes not to the publick advantage. What can be more orderly and deſireable to my purpoſe! Only yet to be more ſure, it is fit, I cite alſo ſome few of his expreſſions. <hi>This is the limit of a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces power, ſo far as he relates to conſcience, for beyond this the conſcience is not bound.</hi> Again, <hi>If a Prince make a Law that is not for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, it hath no ſanction but fear, and no tye upon the Conſcience.</hi> Again, <hi>all ſuch things as are againſt the good of the ſubjects, the Law it ſelf declares it to be no Law, that is, to be more then the ſuperiour hath right, or leave to do.</hi> Again, <hi>Laws that are made to purpoſes beyond thoſe meaſures, do no ways obleige the conſcience. He is the Miniſter of God for good</hi> (ſaith St. Paul) <hi>otherwiſe he is not Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and hath to other purpoſes none of Gods authority, and therefore cannot obleige the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to an active obedience in ſuch, where his power is in incompetent to command.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:39038:17"/>
               <head>CAP. III.</head>
               <p>IT will be time now to come to ſee what he hath objected againſt this Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. The propoſition I am to maintain, and he to oppoſe, is this. That the laws of a common wealth, and particularly an act, or the acts of Parliament in this nation, that are nor for the common good, do not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leige the Conſcience of the ſubject. Though we acknowledge in the mean time, our alleadgiance and ſubjection to his Majeſty as the executioner of the laws, that our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man is bound ſtill, and ſpared through his clemency. It is true that there is a queſtion fallen in, who ſhall be judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which is commanded in a law be for the common good? and I ſhall be ready to ſpeak with the Debator about it, in its order: but in the mean while if it were not for that, what would this reverend man
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39038:17"/>have had to ſay againſt the main determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place he tells us, <hi>that I am a notable inſtance of my Lord B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ns obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that there is a little dry Light in the World.</hi> I remember <hi>Plutarch</hi> hath a tract of ſelf praiſe, and among ſeveral things he hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, one thing he ſayes for it, that there is ſome caſes, and particularly in the caſe of a juſt defence, a man may ſpeak of himſelf, or any thing of his own, as of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Vnder <hi>Plutarchs</hi> Apology, I will ſay I do believe this, that in this particular I am indeed an inſtance that there is but little dry light in the World. For let this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bater ſet himſelf to read as many books as he can, yet I ſuppoſe he may find but few, if any that determine this caſe altogether as I do. I know the ſame Light hath ſhone in on Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> in ſeveral paſſages, when yet it is mixed with ſuch abundance of other matter, that if this Man may be judge he would be ready to cite him as of opinion againſt me in it. There is <hi>lumen ſiccum</hi> therefore, and <hi>lumen maceratum</hi> indeed. I remember the diſtinction well, my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> hath it, in his advancement. And I will ſay yet, that the Light which this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39038:18"/>Debater pretends is macerated Light, Light ſteeped in a prejudiced mind and fetch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the conceptions of others, and moſtly perhaps from that Dr. whoſe cleareſt rayes he wont receive: When the determination which I have offered hath been beaten out from my own thoughts, and will be found that <hi>lumen ſiccum</hi> (notwithſtanding his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe) which is to be attended in this matter. <hi>I am become a fool in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>glorying</hi> (ſays the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>ye have compelled me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place he produces two places of Scripture, that to the <hi>Romans, Wherefore you muſt needs be ſubject not only for wrath but alſo for Conſcience ſake,</hi> and that of Peter, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.</hi> I anſwer, theſe Texts ſpeak of <hi>ſubjection</hi> and not of <hi>obedience;</hi> ſubjection to the Authority, reſiding in the perſons of the Magiſtrate, and if you will in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it ſelf: not obedience which is proper to their commands. I his appears from the firſt and ſecond Verſes. Be <hi>ſubject to the powers that be. He that reſiſteth the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God.</hi> The Powers no doubt are, but the Laws and Commands of men be not I hope the <hi>ordinance of God</hi> with this Man. <hi>VVherefore you muſt needs be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:39038:18"/>It is the ſame word and ſpoken in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the <hi>reſiſtance</hi> before, and in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their perſons: it is not <hi>wherefore</hi> you muſt needs <hi>obey</hi> all their particular commands for Conſcience ſake, when for Conſcience ſake we muſt ſuffer, rather then obey ſome of them. So likewiſe in <hi>Peter, every ordinance of Man,</hi> is every <hi>human crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> in the Original, that is, ſubmit to every ſort of Governor, or Government, whether to the King as ſupream, or others under him. This is plain. Out of theſe Texts therefore may obedience ariſe, from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of not reſiſting, but no direct obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the Conſcience to obey actively can be deduced from hence. Again the Apoſtle tells us in theſe places, that the Magiſtrate is Gods Miniſter for our good, a terror to evil doers, and encourager to well doing, with the like expreſſions. Upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he can be ſuppoſed to command only for the common good, and when a Law or Command of the ſupream Magiſtrate is ſuch, I deny not but it binds the Conſcience no leſs then he. This is ſufficient between us, that no Argument poſſible can be drawn from either of theſe places to ſerve his turn, ſeeing a Law muſt be ſuppoſed to be againſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39038:19"/>the common good, and yet to bind the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience according to him. Moreover, this I muſt ſay ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in is moſt evident that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence indefinite cannot be proved by theſe Texts, becauſe ſome commands of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may be evil, morally evil (as hath been intimated) and we muſt not obey them: or civily evil, and then though we do obey for the Swords ſake, and becauſe we muſt not reſiſt, the Conſcience is not bound in ſuch a Caſe.</p>
               <p>It is therefore a pieviſh obſtinacy in this perſon to perſiſt in theſe following words. <hi>VVe are no conſidering when and in what caſes a Law may ceaſe to obleige and quite alter its Nature, but whether while it doth obleige and is in force it lays a tye on the Conſcience or no? and to this we ſay yes. Laws while they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory bind the Conſcience. Becauſe the Scripture faith ſo, and we ſay ſo indefinitely, becauſe that is the Scriptures language alſo.</hi> Firſt it's certainly falſe that all Laws of Men do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely tye the Conſcience, and therefore the Scripture doth not ſay ſo, nor can ſay ſo, which muſt be granted by him in the caſe of moral evil. Secondly this Debater is utterly loſt that he would not learn of me to diſtinguiſh between the obligation of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39038:19"/>outward man, and the Conſcience; an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation <hi>in foro extertori ſive politico, &amp; in foro interiori ſive conſcientiae.</hi> For it is falſe again that he ſayes we are not conſidering when and in what caſes a Law doth ceaſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leige, for this is the very thing we are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, in reſpect to the Conſcience; and as for the obligation of the outward Man, he hath not yet thought of it. And I ſay as Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> hath again and again, that ſuch a Law, as is not for the common good, hath none of Gods authority, and ſo ceaſes to be any Law as to the Conſcience, when yet we being not to reſiſt, (as is and muſt be often ſaid) the outward man by the Sword may be brought to obey. Thirdly the ſpeaking that Laws while they do obleige (or are of force) do tye the Conſcience, in this Man, who hath not received yet the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the obligation of the outward Man Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litically, and the inward Man which is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, is extreamly ſenſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and conſequently falſe if he underſtood the ſenſe. For Laws that are obligatory or do obleige the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, that is are <hi>Politically</hi> in force, may yet be morally null, as to the Conſcience, that is, obleige it not, when being not for the common good I ſay they are without the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39038:20"/>authority of Gods will. Fourthly there is a manifeſt bar and contradiction in theſe words to his own determination after, if he durſt been plain in it. For here he will be ſo obſtinate to ſay ſtill that human Laws bind <hi>indefinitely,</hi> nay and ſuborn the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to falſe witneſſing in affirming that they ſay ſo, when they ſay only <hi>be ſubject indefinitely</hi> (while he makes <hi>all Laws</hi> (that is <hi>Univerſally</hi>) and <hi>indefinitely</hi> aequivalent here, leaſt he come off upon that word,) which we muſt not do, and yet in the end he is forced to come to confeſſion and acknowledge (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> will tell him ſo, from whom he will borrow that he has) that moral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Lawyers (and I had hoped he were one of the firſt) do determine that human Laws bind <hi>not</hi> in the caſe of <hi>intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grievance.</hi> I have cited theſe words in the way ſomething more acrimoniouſly then any other paſſage hitherto, not that I have cauſe to be angry at them, as I have at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but to ſhew occaſionally how I might take up this Gentleman likewiſe in the reſt of theſe raw Sheets, if I had a mind to exagitate that weakneſs which hitherto (till his eyes be opened farther by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverting the point) is ſuch as may have
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39038:20"/>that epithite given to it at preſent which the Scriptures does in one place give unto <hi>darkneſs</hi> (though I acknowledge his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency otherwiſe,) even <hi>weakneſs that may be felt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the third place he wont allow my little comment on <hi>Paul. The Scripture ſayes the Magiſtrate is Gods Miniſter to us for good. Very true, and the Apoſtle makes that an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument why we ſhould be obedient to him becauſe it is for our benefit. But this Caſuiſt turns the words another way, and makes them an outlet to diſobedience, by taking that to include an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to the general precept of ſubjection, which is in truth nothing but a reaſon to enforce it.</hi> By this paſſage and ſuch as this I take my conjecture of the happineſs of this mans ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, which makes what he ſayes very often to look conſiderable, when if it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon with more thoughts (but that this Man himſelf tells the Apologiſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where that he is <hi>no melancholly Man</hi>) it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies nothing. If there be any thing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial in theſe words it muſt hold, if it he put into others; and then muſt this be denyed that when the Apoſtle tells us the authority the Magiſtrate hath from God is for the peoples good, we may not argue thence that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39038:21"/>he hath no au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hority from God for their hurt. But this arguing is good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this paſſage is but words. For indeed, is there any man that ſerves not <hi>Levi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>than</hi> but God, will maintain that the Magiſtrate hath any au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hority committed to him of God but for the publick benefit? Let this perſon take heed he turns not God into the Devil, and deſtroyes all. If he dare not maintain that, then whatſoever is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded againſt the publick benefit hath no authority to bind the conſcience; and it will be in vain for him to talk idly of the danger he apprehends from my determination which hath none in it, when if he look not better to himſelf he muſt be upon the juſtifying Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and bring ruine upon the World. Again ſuppoſe we build nothing on the very Text, this is a principle in the law of nature, as c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly written in mans heart as that he is a ſociable creature to wit, that the end of Government and Laws, are for the good of the community, and conſequently that there ſhould be none, but for that end. From hence then, that the good of the community being the ſupream Law as the general and ultimate end, of whatſoever is commanded, it muſt irrefragable follow, that whatſoever Law is made or is to be made, it muſt be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39038:21"/>over ruled by this ſupream, and have its obligatory power originally from thence. We know in all Laws or any other things in the world, the inferior muſt give place to the greater or to the <hi>chief.</hi> God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires <hi>ſacrifices</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> both are his Laws, it theſe interfare, mercy muſt be exerciſed and ſacrifice binds not. It is no plainer in the earth that the elements give way from their own natures to ſerve the World, then that the greater or chief obligation muſt vacate the leſs. I might fill a ſide with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, if any elſe could not do it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as this matter then is written with a ſunbeam on the heart of man, and the Apoſtle hath an intimation of it, it is but very ſit and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to reaſon, that we fetch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the ſex from that book he hath touched, that is the book of nature, or this natural Light which will convince every man, that the publick good being the end of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, there can be no power from God but for that end. Again it is true the Apoſtle from hence argues for ſubjection, and he may ſay that he does not argue for any thing elſe. But what then? when <hi>Paul</hi> argues one thing from this truth, may not another argue from thence alſo ſomething too? St.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39038:22"/>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> argues well, the Magiſtrate is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God for our good, therefore we muſt be ſubject: And Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> argues well, and therefore he hath none of his authority for other purpoſes; or that Law that condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth not to the publick good cannot bind the conſcience, becauſe it hath none of Gods authority. Moreover, the Apoſtle argues for ſubjection, and that <hi>indefinite,</hi> but I ſay he argues not, nor may be conſtrued to argue for <hi>obedience indefinite,</hi> and therefore howſoever theſe words tinckle, there is no doubt but we may and muſt make an <hi>outlet</hi> from theſe and the like Texts, that in ſome caſes of the Magiſtrates commands, we may not think our ſelves bound to obey in point of Conſcience, though in regard of non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and ſubjection, there is no diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence does follow in the caſe. We ſay not that this paſſage of the Apoſtle doth include an exception to <hi>ſubjection</hi> for that is Univerſall and indefinite; but we can ſay it muſt include an exception to indefinite or <hi>Univerſal obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> that is as to all the Magiſtrates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, becauſe there may be many of them wicked, unjuſt, or <hi>morally</hi> evil, unto which we are not bound, and conſequently, ſay I, nor to ſuch as are civilly ſo.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:39038:22"/>
               <p>In the fourth place we have this paſſage wherein appears the greateſt weight. <hi>A Law is not meerly the ſignification of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates judgement what is good, but the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his will, that we do it, and God having given him his authority to command us, this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration carries with it an obligatory vertue, to bind us to the execution of his will under the pain of ſin.</hi> As for this, The declaration of the will of the Law-giver does indeed immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately bind the outward Man againſt diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience by <hi>reſiſting,</hi> or to whatſoever is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>ſubjection</hi> (that is it binds us Politically) but as for doing the thing out of conſcience (that is to be bound morally) I like well that this learned Man hath delivered himſelf ſo judiciouſly as to put in that, which is the true &amp; only ground of all the obligation that the Conſcience can be capable of under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Man, and which does adminiſter therefore the ſolution to what he offers. I anſwer then to that branch which he hath of Gods <hi>having given the Magiſtrate his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and we ſay that God hath given the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate no authority to <hi>command</hi> any thing but for the common good, which is a truth for which I need not again quote <hi>Taylor</hi> or <hi>Hooker,</hi> as I remember well that I might, or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39038:23"/>twenty learned Schoolmen perhaps and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to this purpoſe, but that it were not worth my time and trouble to go to their books, Seeing there is indeed ſcarce any truth can ſhine more clearly from the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the end of policy. And the Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt be acknowledged the foundation of all Laws, and the meaſure of their obligation. I do therefore advance here this argument which I think is a ſtone that cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and it is the Sum of my determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Whatſoever is not agreeable to the will of God, or carries not with it Gods authority cannot bind the Conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Conſcience hath an abſolute and immediate dependence on the will of God, and his will is the adaeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate rule of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. But for the Magiſtrate to command any thing that is againſt the common good, is diſagreeable to Gods will: or ſuch a law carries not with it Gods authority. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>go</hi> whatſoever is commanded, or what law ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not conducive to the common good, can not obleige the Conſcience. So that it muſt not be under the pain of ſin, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſence of <hi>wrath,</hi> and neceſſity that we muſt not <hi>reſiſt,</hi> that we actively obey in ſuch a caſe.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:39038:23"/>
               <p>In the laſt place he quotes Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> and I muſt confeſs I ſhall put the leſs truſt hereafter on this man for any matters of controverſie, or caſes of weight for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption he ſeems to have upon one great name, when nothing elſe for ought appears, but Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> having reſolved this caſe, hath given him the confidence to write in ſuch an Imperious faſhion as he hath done theſe ſheets, upon a ſubject whereof he ſeems to have had ſo few thoughts before. As for that Dr. I have read his Lectures <hi>de ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatione conſcientiae, and dejuramento,</hi> and the firſt body of his Sermons. I do believe him an excellent Caſuiſt, and to ſpeak freely where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that excellence lyes, a man of a clear head, but yet not for all that, of ſo <hi>ſearching</hi> a head, nor quite ſo learned as ſuch a one as <hi>Rutherford,</hi> in his way; and by no means on the Earth, of ſo <hi>large</hi> a head, ſo great a wit, and incomparable ſufficiency as Dr. <hi>Taylor.</hi> Well Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> in his ninth <hi>prelection</hi> puts this caſe, what if a Magiſtrate intends only his own profit or ambition in a law? does that bind? he anſwers yes. Becauſe that though the Law-giver may have an ill intention? the Law may tend to the common good. This is well reſolved. In
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39038:24"/>a caſe or two farther then he puts this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what if a law be unprofitable to the publick and ſomething noxious? he anſwers it doth oblige, if the thing may be done without ſin. This reſolution is ill; for if the reaſon of the obligation in the former caſe was good, and the true right reaſon, then when there is not that reaſon, a law obliges not. If we muſt obey out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience when a law does tend to the common good though the Law-givers intention be bad, then though the Law-givers intention be good, if the thing commanded tend not to the publick advantage, the Conſcience muſt not be obliged upon the ſame account. And thus Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> reſolves them both, it is in ſome tranſient paſſages, which I will not ſtand here to find out. But let us hear Dr. <hi>Saunderſons</hi> reaſons. The firſt is, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every man ought to mind what belongs to his part and duty, and not trouble himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout other mens.</hi> But what reaſon is this? it does belong to every man to mind, yea and to conſider and determine whether his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be obliged by a law or no. His ſecond is, <hi>Becauſe our duty is to obey, not to command or ordain.</hi> And what reaſon is this? our duty is to obey if what is commanded
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39038:24"/>be agreeable to Gods will, elſe we cannot be obliged to it in Conſcience though we do it. Theſe two reaſons indeed are twins, both Stillborn, and ſay nothing. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution is ill, and nothing is to be ſaid for it. But what means he by theſe reaſons? The ſubject is to <hi>obey</hi> the Law, not <hi>make</hi> the Law, and he troubles not himſelf to judge whether a thing be good in reference to the Magiſtrates act, but his own. If the law paſs, he may obey it in the outward man whether it be civilly good or no, and not trouble himſelf. But if he come to the point, whether it bind his Conſcience or no, he muſt conſider, whether it hath the authority of God in it, and conſequently, whether both it be Lawfull, and conducive, to the publick advantage. <hi>I may add</hi> (ſays the Debater himſelf,) <hi>though the Magiſtrate ought not to ordain any thing but what is for the peoples good, yet when he doth otherwiſe, it will be more for their good to obey him, then refuſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</hi> I anſwer if the Magiſtrate ought not to ordain any thing but what is for the peoples good, then muſt the ordaining any thing not ſuch, be againſt Gods will. But the Conſcience cannot be obliged by any thing againſt Gods will; or the Conſcience
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39038:25"/>is obleiged by nothing but by Gods will only. <hi>Ergo</hi> no Law or thing commanded us which is againſt the common good can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leige the Conſcience; and ſo hath he cut his own throat here out of ſelf conviction. Nevertheleſs as to what he ſayes elſe, there is one <hi>remove</hi> yet this Debater ſees not, and that is we diſtinguiſh between <hi>non obligation of Conſcience,</hi> and diſobedience; it may be that prudence, and ſuch conſiderations as he urges, or others may prevail with a man in the outward action to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey, when yet he accounts himſelf free from any obligation on his Conſcience.</p>
               <p>There is one thing after this. I feel upon my own mind. I find it not in theſe papers: but I cannot hardly be faithful if I omit it. It is this. Suppoſe a Father or a Maſter, bids me do a thing, I conceive it like to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice his affaires, and e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve it undone: If this Father or Maſter be diſcreet, he will commend me for my care, and be ſo far from charging me with diſobedience as that he will account I have done his will better then he declared it. Upon this I have been apt to determine that the commands of men, and Gods, do thus differ; The one binds unleſs I can give a reaſon which is more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:39038:25"/>for the forbearance then that which appears for obedience: the other binds both as the <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> it ſelf for my action. I think again, ſuppoſe I tell this reaſon to this Father or Maſter, and they will not admit it, but require the thing to be done notwithſtanding, the prejudice which ſhall acrue. If it be in heat I may do well yet to forbear, upon my belief that they will take it well; when their thoughts have cooled, and the Wiſdom herein of many faithful ſervants have been proved. But if I be perſwaded fully that they will be diſpleaſed preſently, and not pleaſed after, it ſeems to me here I am bound to obedience in things not ſinful, though they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to my own and their hurt. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this. In the firſt place it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that a Child, or a Servant is not indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely bound to do every thing they are bid, but that when they have ſuch a reaſon as they judge their Parent or Maſter will be ſatiſfied, and better pleaſed that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the command, they may leave it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. If their reaſon does not ſatiſfie, they may be reckoned in the caſe of ſuch as have no reaſon. In the ſecond place when they have better reaſon to, forbear it then do it,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39038:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>I may hold that they are bound to doing only by vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Authority reſiding in the Parent or Maſters perſon, and that they may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath been ſaid about the Magiſtrate, will that otherwiſe they were free towards God in their Conſciences, who accepts of no other but a reaſonable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>vide. In the third place, <hi>I</hi> offer this, there is a diverſity of Authority. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Parents, and Maſters is not the ſame with that of the Magiſtrates over the People. The Soverainnity in ſome Common wealths is in a ſingle Perſon; in others it may be in the Nobles; in others in the Common body. That Government which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y a Monarchy is either <hi>Deſpotical</hi> or <hi>Royal.</hi> The Government of this Nation is a <hi>Royal Monarchy regulated by laws,</hi> Theſe laws are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by a Corporation of <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nds,</hi> called the <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein the three <hi>Eſtates</hi> are aſſembled to conſult what is for the common good, now though we may ſuppoſe (without granting) that the ſubjects of a deſpotical Government who have no propriety of goods nor liberty of perſon (as children and ſervants are in the houſe) may be bound to do what the Law-giver commands though it be to their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39038:26"/>common diſadvantage, becauſe he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any thing for his will and pleaſure onely and not their goods: yet cannot we in our nation be ſo bound, becauſe it is not to be ſuppoſed that the law-giver does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any thing for his own will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but for the common good altogether. To ſuppoſe otherwiſe is to ſuppoſe a change of the Government, from Royal to Deſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, which is a ſuppoſition to be abhorred <hi>The three Estates are aſſembled</hi> (ſays Sr. <hi>Tho. Smith</hi> de Rep. Ang.) <hi>to conſult what is good,</hi> that is what is for the common good as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and ſo long as this is their general end and intention, and the Law is the will of the Law-giver, it appears that if any thing really be not for the common good, it hath none of their will and intention, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly does lay no obligation on the conſciences of the people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>I Proceed to that determination which he brings in oppoſition to mine, if I can find
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39038:27"/>it, and know what to make of it when it is found. <hi>The caſe</hi> (ſays he about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) <hi>depends on this ſingle point, whether human Laws bind the Conſciences.</hi> In reſolving this, he acknowledgeth a difficulty. <hi>For if on the one ſide we ſay</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not concerned, I beſeech you what is? nothing but our common diſcreton, to help our ſelves out of the reach of the Princes Sword.</hi> So ſays Dr. <hi>Taylor. If Conſcience be not obliged then nothing is concerned but prudence, and care that a man be ſafe from Rods and Axes.</hi> If on the other ſide <hi>we ſay that Conſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce is obliged, then there may follow great perplexities when any thing is commanded, that proves an intollerable grievance.</hi> And this is alſo from Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> who does determine thereupon that <hi>in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death and intollorable grievance human Laws oblige not the Conſcience to obedience.</hi> And what does this Debater determine? why truly when he comes to it at the end, <hi>The morall Divines and Lawyers</hi> (ſays he) do <hi>grant ſo.</hi> Well! Theſe Divines and Lawyers are ſuch as Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> knows, but what ſays this Evangellicall Divine and no Lawyer himſelf? why he has ſaid already that human Laws bind <hi>indefinitely,</hi> and he cannot find in his heart to go from it. Let me ask him then
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:39038:27"/>how comes it to paſs, that he pretends to ſome <hi>better Medium then I have propounded</hi> in this Caſe? Thoſe that ſay human Laws bind not the Conſcience at all, and thoſe that ſay they bind it indefinitely without diſtinction, are both in an extream. I and <hi>Dr Taylor</hi> have a <hi>Medium:</hi> and what <hi>mean</hi> is that which this man will ſet up in oppoſition to us? Here I turn to the place in his ſheets and I find his words come to theſe. <hi>I think good briefly to direct him in a better Medium then any that he hath propounded to find out the ſeverall degrees of ſin againſt human Laws.</hi> Ridiculous! if this perſon would have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered us a better <hi>Medium</hi> to determine the Caſe in hand, we ought to have thankt him: but as for a <hi>Medium</hi> to this purpoſe. what is it to me? Is there any queſtion or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of mine about this in the leaſt throughout the Caſe? If I had a mind to know the difference or degrees of ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt human Laws, I need not come to his I <hi>think good briefly,</hi> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> hath laid down at large <hi>Rules of diſtinction, or the meaſures by which we ſhall prudently conjecture, at the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity or leſſening of the ſin of diſobedience to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Laws.</hi> The truth is, if a man may gueſs at ſuch a thing, this perſon as it is like upon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39038:28"/>the quotation, gets Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> where, in one place there being thoſe <hi>Rules of diſtinction,</hi> and in another he finds, <hi>cautions</hi> for thoſe that reduce into practiſe the rule he had laid down, that <hi>human Laws, not good, oblige not the Conſcience,</hi> he apprehends theſe to be both good materials for the building ſomething againſt me, but when he hath brought them here together into his books, there is no work for ought I ſee will come of them, and he may return them back where he had th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. Here are a parcell of cautions, and notes of degrees of ſin againſt laws, his cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Dr. who giving liberty to the Conſcience in ſome caſes as not bound by human laws are very ſignificant, that we may yet walk unblameably in ſuch caſes: but as for him who gives none, but makes the law of man to bind indefinitely, he hath nothing to do, but to require Univerſal obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, upon the pain of ſin, and can admit of no tranſgreſſion under any caution what ſoever. His rules of diſtinction likewiſe, or of the degrees of ſin againſt human laws, may have good uſe in the <hi>Dr.</hi> but how will they ſerve his purpoſe? the caſe (ſays he) <hi>depends on this ſingle point, whether human laws <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ind the conſcience. that is whether we ſin, if
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39038:28"/>we be not obedient to them?</hi> It follows then when this ſingle point or queſtion is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that they do bind the conſcience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely, and that we do ſin if we obey not, the point determined; and as for the diſcourſe of the degrees of ſin, it is another point, that never comes between us in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy. In the mean while if this be the determination of the point which is ſingle, what is become of the pretended difficulty? There is not the leaſt difficulty in this caſe at all, if that be all the determination.</p>
               <p>Let us ſuppoſe the Negative extream to what he holds, that the conſcience were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver concerned in human laws, and that to his words, <hi>I beſeech you what then,</hi> it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed tho outward man, which politickly is bound, and may not reſiſt, it were a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might require more conſideration, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every mans own ſecurity, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the common diſcretion alone of all men, to keep themſelves only from the danger they threaten, would not be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient preſervative of them: ſo far is this perſon wide who ſpeaks ſo ſlightly, as if we ſhould then <hi>care for the Princes commands not a ſtraw,</hi> when we our ſelves have known while we were boyes, and made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39038:29"/>of the command of any, yet did we obſerve what we were bid more certainly through co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtion, then the moſt of us God knows doe now the divine precepts through the due conſcience we owe to them. And if ſo, there is the more reaſon for this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to be conſiderate, how he bends thus to this other extream, wherein he brings us into that open perplexity, which himſelf ſees, but cannot find the way out, either with his <hi>diſtinction of ſins,</hi> or <hi>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ons</hi> which will not ſuite his reſolution of the queſtion.</p>
               <p>Obedience is not to be denyed (ſayes he in the firſt of theſe cautions) but when a law is againſt the publick good. This is the prime indeed of all the Drs. cautions, &amp; what alone perhaps is enough to be regarded. For when the Dr. and I do both make this to be the determining diſtinction (though he hath not ſpoken indeed ſo dryly of it, through his large invention and multitude of matter as I do) between what <hi>does</hi> and what does <hi>not</hi> oblige the conſcience, in the matter of human laws, if a man does but obſerve this caution, the main of his care is over in this buſines; he neither will, for the ſaving of his own damage, dare to neglect the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſt: nor will he omit obedience
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39038:29"/>but when he can render a reaſon. The reſt of his cautions I will not concern my ſelf in, who have the ſame power to alter theſe, or frame others, to the over ruling truth I offer, as they had who at firſt did frame them; but as for this which I have named, the very propoſing of it in the firſt place, when the Dr. brings it in after others, doth ſeem to carry in it ſome conviction on this perſon (when otherwiſe it no wayes ſerves his purpoſe) that if a thing be not for the common good, it cannot in good earneſt bind the conſcience.</p>
               <p>For his diſtinction or degrees of ſin, the main deſign of oppoſing my determination thereby being fruſtrate, let us ſee to what uſe elſe he can put it. That may ſtand him perhaps in ſome ſtead for his own excuſe, which will not ſtand his reader in any for his ſatisfaction. This Debater then we know in his late books, having deſigned to expoſe the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> to deriſion and contempt, as much as he could, for the withdrawing the people from Schiſm, and recalling them to Church (to ſpeak ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly of his end) hath thought it fit in his firſt book to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gin his charge of theſe men with the breach of the <hi>Oxford</hi> Act, the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39038:30"/>charge is very high upon this, that they are not good Chriſtians, not Miniſters of Chriſt. To this end perſiſting in the ſame mind, through his books even to this Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of his appendix, he gives us theſe notes for the diſcovering of the greatneſs of a ſin againſt human Laws, the Iſſue whereof comes to this, that though there may be ſeveral Inſtances of perſons beſides living in the breach of other ſtatutes the ſin of the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> againſt this act, muſt come under thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more hainou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aggravations, that when ſuch are excuſed, yet as for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, <hi>we may find he had reaſon to ſay what he did,</hi> not to uſe any other then his own words. And what is that then he will acknowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hath ſaid? <hi>I never ſaid that no man can be a good Chriſtian that tranſgreſſeth an Act of Parliament: nor that every tranſgreſſion of a ſtatute is a deadly ſin: Thoſe are inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his own upon occaſion of a ſingle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which I gave of defyance to a Law wherein ſome men live, mark my words, from whence he draws as Uninerſall propoſition.</hi> And does <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſay ſo. Let me turn to his book and ſee how he can come of thus. The <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> ſpeaking of his Miniſter, the matter is thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Uſhered in; <hi>How can he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:39038:30"/>be a Miniſter of Chriſt</hi> (<hi>ſays</hi> the Conformiſt) <hi>who is diſobedient to his Sovereign, whom Chriſt blas to obey?</hi> And then Inſtancing wherein, he urges this <hi>Oxford</hi> Act, and concludes, <hi>therefore he is not a good ſubject, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no good Chriſtian or Miniſter of Chriſt.</hi> Let any man judge here whether theſe words, <hi>How can he be a Miniſter of Chriſt who is diſobedient to his Sovereign?</hi> be not aequivalent with this propoſition. No man that is diſobedient to his Sovereign is a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt. With what face then can he accuſe me with drawing an Univerſal propoſition from his words, when there is one expreſs in the book, and from thence this concluſion is deduced? I <hi>never ſaid,</hi> does he mean theſe are not his very words? away I nor do I ſay they are, but does not what he ſayes amount plainly to this very ſence? I prove it. <hi>Therefore</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>he is not a good ſubject, and conſequently not a good Chriſtian.</hi> I argue with him from hence this perſon is a man of Reaſon and Logick. Here then is a concluſion, no concluſion can be good but from an Univerſal propoſition. This Univerſal propoſition muſt be this, that whoſoever i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſobedient to his Soveraign, or tranſgreſſes an Act of Parliament is no
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39038:31"/>good Chriſtian. And the Univerſal propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in his book is this, which howſoever we underſtand (to help him out) that he means, whoſoever tranſgreſſes any act of Parliament in ſuch a high and hanious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the Non-conformiſt does the <hi>Oxford</hi> act, yet ſtill is a Univerſal propoſition: either this perſon therefore muſt renounce the words in his book as illogically or falſly concluded, which yet he cannot do, neither but by acknowledging the univerſallty, and the denying the truth of the propoſition: or elſe he muſt be aſhamed here of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt accuſation of me, who have done but right to him. But if this denial will not ſerve him, he is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute of other ſhifts. <hi>There is no occaſion</hi> (ſays he) <hi>for thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> queſtion whether every tranſgreſsion of a Statute be no leſs then a deadly ſin, unleſs he is of opinion that all ſins are equal.</hi> By theſe words he does ſeem manifeſtly here to make ſome eſcape upon that term <hi>deadly ſin,</hi> and then he muſt diſtinguiſh between <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>deadly ſin,</hi> which no Proteſtant will allow him to do, who ſay that all ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is mortal; &amp; there was nothing elſe intended by a deadly ſin, but a ſin that deſerves or makes one guilty of death. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if this Perſon can tell me of any little
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39038:31"/>ſin, in oppoſition to a greater, which a man may knowingly and willfully live in, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance unto death, and it ſhall not damne him, or do him hurt, then I ſhall like well of his comming off here, upon this term: but if he cannot, then will not this ſerve, he muſt ſeek another ſhift. And what is that in the next place, for he is brought here into a ſhuffling condition, that is plain? why we muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a wilful living only, in the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a law, and the living in the <hi>defiance</hi> of it. <hi>The inſtance I have</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is of the defiance of a law in which ſome men live.</hi> This word <hi>defiance</hi> therefore he hath up three or foure times, beſides the cotation in the margent, and bidding us <hi>mark the word.</hi> But I pray why muſt the Waggoner that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day tranſgreſſes the law concerning his Waggon, or any other the like inſtance, be accounted with this man only to live in the tranſgreſſion of that law. and the Non-conformiſt in his non obſervance of the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> act be adjudged to live in the <hi>defiance</hi> of it? Alas! who does not ſee here into what a pitiful ſhifting caſe he is driven? or who does not perceive what is worſe, that is, the animoſity, peviſhneſs, or overbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:39038:32"/>(to ſpeak with candour) of the man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mind againſt the Non-conformiſt, which does hinder him the coming off here with that ingenuity as he ſhould do, which is by confeſſion of ſeveral of his imprudent ſpeeches, and craving pardon for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance he hath uſed. But in the laſt place, there are ſtill degrees of ſin, and the man that breaks other laws may not be ſo deeply guilty as he that lives in the breach of the act at <hi>Oxford.</hi> Let us ſee then what he can alledge for this. <hi>The more needful a Magiſtrate judges a thing to be done or avoided or the more his will is ſet upon it, the greater or leſs is the ſin of him who breaks ſuch a Law.</hi> Now he argues from the <hi>Preface</hi> and the <hi>Penalty</hi> of the <hi>Oxford</hi> act, how much the will of the law-giver is ſet upon the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of that act, unto which I anſwer, beſides that Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> doth toll us that the greatneſs of the penalty doth ſometimes ſhow the ſmalneſs of a thing that is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den (as tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which elſe would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded) and not the haniouſneſs of the tranſgreſſion: it does appear that the will of the law givers in that act, was ſet upon the <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> taking the oath there prepared, as that they would have enforced
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39038:32"/>them to by ſo great and preſent a danger, and was the thing which ſeemed to them ſo apt to prevent, the evil ſuppoſed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, when as for their living within five miles of a corporation otherwiſe, we cannot think the minds of the <hi>Majority</hi> to be at all engaged in it. Now this Debater ſhould have endeavoured to give the <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> ſatisfaction in referrence to his taking the Oath, if he would have ſerved the State according as the will of the law-givert were then ſet, but this was a task which he hath declined, although he was put upon it, and directed to their objections, in the <hi>defence of the propoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is ſomthing after this, which may be ſaid, that though this diſtinction, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of ſins will ſtand him in no advantage for the oppoſing my determination, or juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his cenſure of the <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> to be no good Chriſtian, yet may it be of uſe to him to alleviate the harſhneſs of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the main, that human laws do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the Conſcience ſo as without diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation he that obſerves them not, does ſin. Hence when he propoſes the caſe of a law-giver enjoyning a thing to ſome particular good, for the publick, and it appears that he
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39038:33"/>is miſtaken, this Debater does continue ſtill (ſuch an obedient Soul has he above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) that <hi>though he be not bound to be of the lawgivers judgement, yet does he take himſelf bound</hi> (he means bound in Conſcience) <hi>to follow his will even while it were better for the publick it were other wife or dained.</hi> There are caſts we know ſometimes wherein by the change of things and occaſions (as in Seiges) that which was for the publick good does ſuddenly turn to its hurt. In ſuch inſtances we are not to obey a law ſayes <hi>Aquinas,</hi> which Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and there is no doubt to me in the Caſe, where the lawgiver is miſtaken in a matter, the like reaſon ought to prevaile. But if he be thus reſolved, let us know how the degrees of ſin will help him out at a need. Let me ſuppoſe a poor man who is render in his Conſcience and fears God, coming to this reverend Perſon and telling him this caſe. His Grand-father got a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mony, and built him a ſmall Cottage on ſuch a waſte ground, his Father lived in it, and beſtowed more coſt of it, and hath left it him, where he and his wife and child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren have lived comfortably uppon his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: but now it hath ſo hapned, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39038:33"/>the other day at his Maſters where he wrought, he heard one read a certain book called the <hi>Friendly Debate</hi> where he perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, about the very begining that the Author was of the mind that a man could not live in the breach of the Law of the Land, and be a good Chriſtian: and he hath underſtood long by his Father that it is againſt the Law for any cottage to be erected withot four a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres of ground belonging to it. Upon this he being afraid of his condition in regard of his open living in a known wilful tranſgreſſion of a ſtatute of the Realm, wherein he cannot think but that it is a very plain <hi>defiance of a-Law</hi> as that book ſpeaks, he is come to him to ſee what he can offer for the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eiving his Conſcience. If this author here deal round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainly with the man, he muſt tell him that there is no remedy but he muſt pull down his houſe, and he and his wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be turned to beging, rather then by his living in a known ſin without amendment he ſhould be damned. It he deal otherwiſe, then he may tell him that though indeed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tranſgreſſion of a human Law be ſin, yet there are degrees of ſin, and this ſin of his is a leſſe ſin then that of the <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt</hi> living in the breach of the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Act and therefore he ſhould be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39038:34"/>of good comfort and go home in peace. I pray now will this indeed ſerve a Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious man: It is nothing to him that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's ſin is greater then his, he is to look to his own ſoul, and if he lives in the leaſt ſin with full knowledge and conſent, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens his heart in it, he cannot ſee how he ſhould be ſaved. So that unleſs you ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, and that upon good ground, that every tranſgreſſion of a Law is not ſin, and then ſhew him how his tranſgreſſion is but ſuch a one you are not able to ſtand him in any ſtead in his Caſe. I remember a text of our Lord which I haue often thought upon, that <hi>by a mans words he ſhall be juſtified and by his words he ſhall be cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed.</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes were men very holy in their profeſſion and did tye very heavy burthens upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but when they were to perform the ſame themſelves they were it is like back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enough: our ſaviour Chriſt therefore meets with them, for theſe ſhews without reality, and words without performance. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you that for every Idle word a man ſhall ſpeak he ſhall give on account for it at the day of judgement.</hi> The word <hi>Idle</hi> in the Original as without work ſays <hi>Cauſabone de verborum uſu</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is contracted of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:39038:34"/>every Idle word is every word without deed; and muſt import thus much (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it does more) that when men make ſtrict profeſſions, and determine ſo rigid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in points of duty, and do not anſwer their own dictates and ſayings, let them take heed leſt by their words (leaſt <hi>ex ore tuo</hi>) as being <hi>Idle</hi> words they bring not themſelves into a juſt condemnation. I will therefore adviſe this worthy perſon, and all men in reſolving Caſes of Conſcience that they take heed of ſetting down any matter for the binding of others, then according to which in their own practiſe they dare be content to be judged by. The determining the obligation of human Laws Indefinitely on the Conſcience is more then any mortall can bear. For my own part I will proteſt that whilſt I allow the Conſcience to be bound, by the Law of men when thoſe Laws tend to the common good, yet do I not hereby cut my ſelf of from the reſerve of any liberty that may ariſe to me from a farther diſquiſition: although I count it but neceſſary both to give my reaſon why in ſincerity I hold ſo, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver my conception of that obligation.</p>
               <p>It is a ſaying of the Antients, a man is not born for himſelf only, but for his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39038:35"/>which is not writ only in <hi>Cicero,</hi> but in the heart of all men, for this is a truth throughout the earth, and delivered by God all along his word, while he makes our own ſelves to be the rule of our carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Neighbours, that we mind not our own things only, but every one the things of others. Though we ſtudy and ſeek the tranquillity and peace of thoſe with whom we live: and conſequently in all Societies and Communities, we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the publick concern, even above our particular advantage. Theſe are general moral precepts which are writ I ſay in the heart of man, and to be proved in Gods word. The Magiſtrate I account now is Gods Miniſter, to conſider of, and then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and appoint the particular things or inſtances wherein every one in their ſeveral places are ſerviceable in theſe duties and ends; and upon that deſignation of the particular things, the obligation flows from thoſe general precepts of God, upon the Conſcience, for their obſervation. I ſay there is the general Inſtitution of God for Societies, and that men in ſociety ſhall mind and endeavour in their place the publick concern, and not their own only. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39038:35"/>is his commiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted Officer to deſign appoint or ſet apart, and ſo declare the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances or particular things which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to this good of the community which they all are bound to intend upon the deſignation, appointment or declaration of theſe things, the obligation flows immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from the general inſtitution of God upon the Conſcience for the obſerving of them, when there could flow none elſe from theſe particulars themſelves. The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar laws or things themſelves we know are not the precepts of God, and the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is obliged only by Gods will; but the general inſtitution of ſociety, and that we ſhould ſeek and endeavour in our place the good of the Publick as our own, and above our own, in ſuch particulars as be conducive truly to that end, is of God; and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate (I ſay) according to his office de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning theſe particulars, we come (not <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione conſequentis,</hi> or <hi>abſoluté,</hi> only becauſe ſuch things commanded, but <hi>ratione conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ntiae,</hi> or <hi>ex hypotheſi,</hi> becauſe ſuch things commanded do come under the divine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution) to have the Conſcience bound to their performance. From hence it follows likewiſe that if theſe inſtances or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39038:36"/>do not indeed come under the ſervice of theſe general duties or end, ſuch a law is to be lookt upon as cut off from Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and ſo can have no authority de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to it from God, for the obliging the Conſcience of any, when yet the outward man (out of the caſe of ſin) is ſtill acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be bound. The particular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Magiſtrate does (I ſay) bind the outward man: but the general inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or the moral duty in general of ſeeking the welfare of the Publick, and not our own only, is that which binds the Conſcience which otherwiſe were not bound.</p>
               <p>As for the fifth Commandement, which requires honor and obedience (ſuch as is meet) to our ſuperiours, I do not here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh it from, but include it in this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral inſtitution, for that command muſt be underſtood as a comprehenſive thing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining in it the whole <hi>commiſsion,</hi> the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour hath from God, which granting him his power to command, doth alſo ſet the bounds and limitations to that power, that he command no other things, or no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then as he hath appointed: and upon ſuppoſition that the ſuperior acts only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his commiſſion, that is, according
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39038:36"/>to his preſcribed duty, or rule in civil things, this Commandement of God do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lay an obligation on the ſubject to obey him out of Conſcience. If you will ſay upon this that the Magiſtrate hath a derived authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from God, for this very act of determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the material obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct of our obedience, and therefore beſides the obligation which flows from his inſtitution when the matter is determined, the Conſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged from the Magiſtrats determination it ſelf, by vertue of that derived authority from him, I have no need to gain ſay it, and whether you will make it a double obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or an obligation from a double cauſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or a mixt obligation divine and human, it matters nothing to our diſpute, ſo long as Gods authority in the things commanded, or his allowance that they be commanded be firſt acknowledged, before we look upon the Conſcience to be indeed concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them. This is certain, every autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that is <hi>derived</hi> muſt be <hi>limited,</hi> and that according to the will of him from whence it is derived. The authority God reſerves in his own hands is that alone which is unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and infinite. Now the limits God hath ſet the Magiſtrate as to the determining
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39038:37"/>the particulars of his ſubjects duty (which is his power of making laws) comes to this, that he chooſe them only out of that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral matter that is conducive to the end of government, the publick good (that is to obſerve the rule of things political): If he ſhall therefore appoint any particular things for his own profit, pleaſure, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, which come not under this general matter, (to wit, <hi>quae habet rationem publici commodi</hi>) as God hath preſcribed, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that he acts not according to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and ſo can have no power derived from thence, for thoſe acts or laws, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently however ſuch laws do bind us in <hi>his courts,</hi> they are of no validity <hi>in the court of Conſcience.</hi> We will acknowledge in whatſoever he commands an authority divine for his <hi>Office</hi> and ſo if he will inflict the penalty we muſt not reſiſt. But we can not acknowledge Gods authority in this or that <hi>exerciſe of his office.</hi> that we ſhould do the thing out of Conſcience. In ſhort, we are indeed bound upon the <hi>penalty of his law,</hi> (if you will) but we are not bound up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>pain of ſin,</hi> to obey the Magiſtrate in every caſe.</p>
               <p>I muſt profeſs here in the words of truth,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39038:37"/>and ſoberneſs that ſo far as ſo mean a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as I am can di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is a great deal of darkneſs hath ſpread it ſelf upon the face of the earth, and more eſpecially over many learned men, who when they have forſaken that light which they have flowing immediately from God, on their hearts to to ſeek unto the Ciſterns of others works and books, they have been not only miſled themſelves, but bereft us of many truths of the cleareſt evidence, and greateſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuch as this particular<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y concerning the obligation of human laws, how, when and how far the Conſcience of man (which belongs directly only to the Regiment of Gods its or can be bound by them. If we will therefore but go as near as we can to the fountain, and look into our own minds, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all which God ſhines according to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral meaſure with his light, though he influence but ſome with his ſaving grace, we may find, that as we are inſtructed in matters of <hi>Religion</hi> to ſeek unto ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral revelation, and ſo to account that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is agreeable to the rule of Gods word is obliging to the Conſcience, and what is not cannot oblige us as worſhip: and as in matters of <hi>morality,</hi> what is and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39038:38"/>what is not agreeable to the law of nature, does or does not oblige us as virtue or vice: ſo in theſe matters which are of a <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val</hi> or political concern only, we do find that the rule which God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lmighty hath written in the heart for us to judge by, and is the ſupream law in ſuch matters, (which in words alſo is famouſly acknowledged) is the common good: ſo that according as any thing commanded in human laws is agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or not, to that rule which is Gods rule for theſe things, the Conſcience is bound or not bound by the ſame. Nay as things are not only religiouſly or morally good and evil according as they agree and not agree with the word of God, and the moral law in the heart, but the more or leſs they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the rule, the more or leſs good or evil are they: ſo the more or leſs any thing commanded in a law doth agree with the ſupream rule of God, or law, in theſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical things, by ſo much the greater or leſs is the ſin of not obſerving them. So ſhort indeed is this Perſon and others in their notes of the degrees of ſin againſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man laws, that the formal difference it ſelf of theſe aggravations or diminutions in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the conſcience (whereof alone Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:39038:38"/>ſhould ſpeak when this mans differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the will of the law giver, belongs to the Lawyer) is not conſidered. And now when it hath pleaſed God Almighty by ſo inconſiderable a veſſel, and in ſuch a kind of careleſs and unregarded expreſſion, (which others may mend) that the exellency of the truth may appear to be the more from him, to deliver to the world this law of his, to govern and reſolve men in theſe caſes, I do not know how few, or how many there be that will receive it. When <hi>Moſes</hi> went up to God into the Mount, and brought down the law of the two Tables, it was a glorious matter? there is no man can go up to God now in that manner: but every one may go to him, (if we ſearch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him who is not far from any of us as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks) as he dwels in that light which he hath put into our hearts, and from thence (as one who hath been converſing there rather then with the <hi>videturs</hi> of men) have I brought you down this law, or rule of his will in Politicalls, which though the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men no where, even amongſt the moſt ſavage, is without, yet have they ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of it ſo little hitherto, that wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vain in their own imaginations, they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39038:39"/>have not underſtood, when they have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, that this indeed is the ſupream law to all others that are human, by which they muſt be tryed, approved overruled, and according to which, and to which alone, can the Conſcience of any be obliged in their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience which they yield to theſe maters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CA. V.</head>
               <p>THere remains the laſt thing I have to do, which is the ſurveigh of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baters exceptions, or other paſſages not yet conſidered, and to ſay ſomething to them according as they are of moment. This general does contain the principle thing the Debater ſtands upon, and which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirers the larger field for my debate with him, I ſhall devide that one buſineſs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore into three ſucceding Chapters, and leave a laſt for the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:39038:39"/>
               <head>CAP. VI.</head>
               <p>THe great and principal exception he hath, and which will deſerve the pains, is upon a queſtion which comes in as neceſſary to be askt upon my determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and it is this. It being ſuppoſed, and to be granted, that the <hi>will</hi> of God is that alone which does oblige the Conſcience, and that according as a thing commanded in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Laws does conduce to the pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ick good or not, ſo is it agreeable or not to his will: the queſtion is who ſhall be judge, whether a thing commanded by a Law be for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good or no, and conſequently agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Gods will and obligatory to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. I anſwer every Man muſt be Judge on neceſſity himſelf in reference to his own action. I prove this. Every Man muſt judge of his own actions whether they be agreeable to the will of God or no. But to judge whether a thing commanded by a Law be agreeable to Gods will, is to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be conducive to the common good
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39038:40"/>or not. Therefore every Man is judge himſelf, whether a thing commanded be for the publick good or no, in reference to his own action. Again, to judge whether we are bound in Conſcience to any thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in a Law, is to judge whether it have Gods authority or not. But a Law or any thing commanded by a Law hath Gods authority or not, according as it is conducive to the common good. Therefore a Man muſt judge, whether that which is commanded him in a Law be for the common good or not, to judge whether he be bound or not bound to it in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. I muſt needs ſay there are ſome have had occaſion to be more ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve this queſtion, then otherwiſe they have deſired. We have had late impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and thought many times in what ſenſe they might be taken. We have come quickly to ſee, if they be taken, it muſt not be in any ſenſe of our own, we can frame, which were moſt looſe; but it muſt be in the impoſers meaning. This meaning is not certain, but ſome have believed thus and ſome otherwiſe. In the upſhot then this is that I have been brought, in my laſt thoughts, to conclude, that if a Man after the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:39038:40"/>beſt means he can uſe for the underſtanding the Impoſers meaning, can take what is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in that ſence which he verily believes in his own heart to be their meaning, he ſhall do well and ought to take it; if he cannot, he muſt for bear and chooſe to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. Being thus prepared in order to the determining a mans own act, about the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an impoſition, when the queſtion lyes upon the meaning of the Law-giver, and the ſubject I count being changed only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his generall end in this, I had no cauſe to ſtick here, where there is but one and the ſame anſwer to be given to all ſuch queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. To wit, that notwithſtanding there may be ſeverall good cautions of thinking reverendly of our ſuperiours judgments, and not leaning too much on our own, with the like words uſed in the way, we muſt come to this reſult at laſt, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as every man for his own part (after the beſt enquiry or exerciſe of his reaſon he can make) does believe in his very Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence whether the thing commanded in a Law be for the publick good or no, I mean it in reference to his own doing it, that is moſt plainly according as he believes in his own ſoul that the doing the thing which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:39038:41"/>is commanded (by his example or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) is conducive to the publick good or not, ſo muſt he account it agreeable or not to Gods will, and his Conſcience accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly be bound, or looſed in regard to the performance.</p>
               <p>I will convince the Debater from his own mouth and from the thing it ſelf.</p>
               <p>From his own mouth we have a Caſe hath fallen very luckily before mentioned. What if Magiſtrate miſtake in a Law, and the matter be not conducive to that end for the publick he ordained it? He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers he is not bound to be of the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates opinion, but may judge it better the Law were otherwiſe, yet thinks he is bound to obey it. But if this man and ſo another may be, and is, of a contrary o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion to the Magiſtrate, that the thing commanded is not for the publick benefit, as he acknowledges in that Caſe of his own putting, then hath he acknowledged in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect all that for which he cavills ſo much at me upon my anſwer to this queſtion.</p>
               <p>For the thing it ſelf, In the firſt place no mortal man on Earth, can have power to make me, or him, or any underſtand, to think, or believe otherwiſe then we do. If
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:39038:41"/>I do think then, that ſuch a thing command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be not for the common good, ſo I ſhall think, and muſt think do what the Magiſtrate can, or my ſelf either. And it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do believe ſo then do I judge or believe that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods will, and conſequently that I am not bound in Conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. If you ſay I ſhould not think ſo, it is unlawful to judge ſo, you contradict this man, who ſays, he is <hi>not bound abſolut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly to be of the Law-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers opinion, that all ſuch things are for the publick good as he decrees;</hi> which is as truly, as ſtoutly ſaid againſt himſelf, for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will not bear it to be otherwiſe. In the ſecond place, Conſcience is a faculty which God hath put into Man, to judge of his own actions, in reference to his approving or condemning him for them. Whatſoever actions then are accountable unto God at the great day, are to be judged at preſent by Conſcience. We are accountable now no doubt to God for our <hi>civil</hi> actions, as well as others; and when in matters that are civil, thoſe things have or have not his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, as they do, or do not conduce to the common good, it follows that every man muſt judge of the things commanded him, whether they be or they be not to the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39038:42"/>common good, that he may be accountable unto God, according to what he is bound or not bound in Conſcience by them. In the third place our <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Divines in their cont overſy which the <hi>Papiſt Do judice,</hi> do allow to every man a judgement of private diſcretion which is the ſame with this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Conſcience, that what means ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we uſe for our information, we muſt be the laſt judges our ſelves of the things we do, whether they are agreeable to Gods will or not, and according to our own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief muſt reſolve upon the practiſe or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of them. It ſeems to me now a thing unreaſonable and injurious unto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, if we ſhall take away from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject this judgement of private diſcretion in things that are <hi>political</hi> which we cannot but allow them in all other their <hi>morall</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> actions. If there be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible judge in <hi>Civils</hi> we may expect one in <hi>religions</hi> matters. But if there be no <hi>Pope</hi> nor Counſels but may erre in their Canons, there are no Law-givers but may erre in their Laws, and there is no cauſe why any ſhould indeed be more ſhy of granting the ſubject this judgement of diſcretion in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to what the Prince hath <hi>Enacted,</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:39038:42"/>any more then what the Church hath <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared,</hi> but only that they could not ſo well tell the rule to judge of things <hi>Civill</hi> as they could to judge of <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>morall Precepts.</hi> As God therefore hath given us the Scriptures for a rule of religion, that when any thing is required of us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or practiſe as neceſſary to Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or our ſalvation, we may and are to try it, by this rule, and can be obliged thereby no farther then we do judge it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to this rule: and as in morals he hath given the law of nature for our rule: ſo hath the Almighty given to man his rule alſo in things politicall (which he hath written in his fleſhly tables, as ſure as there is any law of nature, and that is Gods will, as the ſcripture is) whereby the Laws of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Common-wealth are to be tryed and judged, the Law-giver being accountable to God according as he acts by it, and the People obliged in Conſcience, ſo far to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his will as he commands agreeably to it: and this Rule or Law as I have before ſaid, is the common good. Things are religiouſly good or evill as they agree or agree not with the Scriptures. Things are moraly good or evill as they agree or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39038:43"/>not with the Law of nature. Things politically good or evill as they agree or agree not to the publick advantage. If I am commanded any thing about my reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion I will go to the Scripture, if that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands me otherwiſe I cannot obey it. I will go to the morall Law in matters of vertue and vice. In politicall things, or things required by human Laws, I muſt go to this rule I have propoſed: I muſt judge of them as good or evill in their kind by that. If my doing the thing will not anſwer the rule, I am not bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to active obedience. In the laſt place if this be not granted, when you allow the ſubjects to be reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able agents in things <hi>religious,</hi> or <hi>morall,</hi> that may bring what is ſuperiour command's of that nature to the reſt of Gods will, you turn them into bruites in things <hi>civil</hi> while they may bring what they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to no teſt, in relation to their own actions. If you deny me my judgement of private diſcretion, you will not let me act as a man. Indeed this perſon will have the liberty to judge otherwiſe then the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate does, and yet be bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to obey, which is to be beneath a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:39038:43"/>bruite, for the beſt act ſpontaneouſly, and follow the dictates of their ſenſe, if they be not hindred. But this man will have his judgement one way, that the thing is not good, and his will and actions another way, and that not upon conſtraint from without, but upon the principle of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is a contradiction againſt all good ſence. But as for others and this man too otherwhere (who makes it a <hi>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our ſelves in the throne to determine other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe concerning the publick welfaer, then the proper judge of it doth,</hi> ſo conſiſtent is he with himſelf, and ſuch need hath he to be angry if one adviſe him to be more <hi>reflective<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> on what he writes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that will not let us have a judgement different from the Lawgiver, and ſo to act only upon theirs, they make men to become Horſe as the and the Mule, upon whom the rider gets up, and they muſt go on, the <hi>why,</hi> and the <hi>whither</hi> as the driver pleaſes. But if this be the Iſſue which this mans opinion will lead us to, and this ſon of <hi>Circe</hi> ſhould expect by the conjuration of theſe few leaves to transforme us preſently out of our humanity, that we ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be governed hence forward without, the exerciſe of our own reaſon, or aſſent
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39038:44"/>that is, not to act out of election, but to be moved in civill obedience only as we are <hi>driven,</hi> we ſhall have little cauſe to be very forward to hearken to him. He may lay down his Penn and take a Whip in his hand and go Whiſtle.</p>
               <p>But let us hear his exceptions to this anſwer. <hi>Who ſhall be judge whether a Law be for the publick good or no. His anſwer is ready at his Tongues end, for he needs not go deep for it.</hi> The <hi>Magiſtrate muſt judge, what is for the publick good for the making the Law, and we muſt judge as to our obedience to it. Then which it is hard to write any thing more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate and dangerous.</hi> I do acknowledge this to be my judgement, and for which I have offered here ſome reaſons, and it is not his ſaying this anſwer is inconſiderate and dangerous ought to prejudice it, if it be well adviced, and there be no danger indeed in it. For neither doth this man know the previous thought on other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon which this hath been ſet down: nor hath he yet underſtood the ſtate of my opinion right, that he ſhould charge it with any of thoſe conſequences, as are but the Lyons, and the Bears, the Chariots and the Armies, that fly in the Clouds of his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39038:44"/>own Immagination. <hi>But let us hear the reaſon of this wonderful deciſion which he hath as ready as he had his anſwer. Becauſe ſaith he every man is made by God the judge of his own actions, I cannot for my life ſee how that follows from this, though I have put his reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the plaineſt form that ever I could.</hi> It is pitty but this mans life ſhould be ſaved, and therefore I will tell him my reaſoning Thoſe Laws, I was ſhewing, which be not for the common good are not agreeable to Gods will, or have not his Authority, and ſo bind not the Conſcience. The queſtion upon this was as it is ſet down, and the anſwer and the reaſon with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the words following. <hi>Becauſe God hath made every man judge of his own actions, and conſequently of all circumſtances, whether they are agreeable or not to his will for his forbearing or doing of them.</hi> If God then hath made every man judge of thoſe things which he is to do in all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whether they be agreeable or not to his will, then muſt he judge whether thoſe things that he is commanded to do in human Laws be for the common good or no, becauſe thoſe Laws only are agreeable to his will (I had laid down before) which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39038:45"/>are for the common good, and thoſe that are not are devoid of his Authority and bind not the Conſcience. This I deny not to be my very ſubſtance, and as the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is manifeſt, and will appear ſo (I doubt not) to the indifferent, ſo muſt it not be thought to be inculcated too often, either there, or here, ſeeing no man can ſtand ſafe in diſpute, but he that knows what is, and when he is upon his foundation. For the mans diſdainful expreſſions I have (I account) my ſatisfaction, and he his ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reproof, that he hath no more cauſe for them. <hi>It is not ſence to ſay the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate muſt judge what is for the publick good in reference to his act of making the Law, and we in reference to ours of obedience to it; for he doth not only judge but enjoyn, when he makes a Law; which leaves us no liberty but to judge whether his will and Gods do not claſh together.</hi> And why is not this ſenſe, what reaſon is this that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is not ſenſe? if he could have ſaid the Magiſtrate does enjoyn, and not judge at all before he enjoyns it, then he might have pretended to ſay thus. But if the Magiſtrate muſt not enjoyn any thing before he hath conſidered, and judges it to be for the common good, and if he doth
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39038:45"/>enjoyn any thing that is not for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good he hath no Authority from God for it, then does it appear neceſſary, that we do conſider likewiſe, and judge whether it be for the common good, and have his Authority, or elſe we cannot be bound in Conſcience to it. And thus you ſee very good ſenſe, evidence and fulneſs in this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the queſtion and that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates will, declaration of his will, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning a thing, does not take away our liberty and duty, to conſider when he hath enjoyned it, whether we be yet in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in obliged, or in prudence only, and the outward man to obedience. The miſtake of this perſon is that he thinks we may not judge of a Law, but only whether it be <hi>againſt</hi> Conſcience, when we muſt no doubt judge alſo whether it be obliging to Conſcience, or otherwiſe how ſhall we make Conſcience of it? We are not to judge only whether it <hi>claſpes</hi> with Gods will, but whether it <hi>agrees</hi> with it. If the Magiſtrates will be not againſt Gods will, yet if it hath not his will and authority with it, it is not obligatory to the Conſcience. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates will binds not aſunder from Gods, In morals the caſe is not thus, whatſoever
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39038:46"/>is not <hi>according</hi> to Gods will is againſt it: But in civil and indifferent things a thing may not be againſt his will, that is againſt any moral precept (as our obedience I ſpeak of to ſome human Laws) and yet have none of his Authority for it. Thus prudence, the preſervation of my ſelf, and the Magiſtrates honour, may prevail with me to do a thing which I think otherwiſe I have no obligation to do in my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>I will yet add. I diſtinguiſh my <hi>obediénce,</hi> and my <hi>obedience out of Conſcience,</hi> or my obedience out of other <hi>generall rerſons,</hi> and my obedience out of Conſcience, to this <hi>particular command.</hi> I do not reſolve my <hi>obedience,</hi> into a judgement of private diſcretion whether a Law be for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good or no, for I can apprehend eaſily that when God hath required the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate to make no Law but according to this rule, no unjuſt, or unprofitable Law, he hath not yet commanded that I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver obey ſuch a Law. I may obey out of a generall implicit apprehenſion of duty; or a ſingular love to my ſuperiors perſon, for fear of his diſpleaſure: to avoid the danger of the Law: or out of ſeverall pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiall
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39038:46"/>conſiderations, regarding the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, my ſelf, or others: when yet If I come to the point, whether I am bound in Conſcience to do the particular thing commanded, that is whether there lyes a divine obligation on me as well as that from the Law to do it I am on neceſſity then to examine it, by the rule which God hath ſet me, and that being no other but the <hi>common good</hi> in politicalls, I muſt reſolve my <hi>obedience out of Conſcience</hi> into this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when I reſolve my <hi>prudentiall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> otherwiſe. It may ſuffice me therein, ſo long as the thing is not ſinfull, that I am obliged by man. It may be but very rare if. I queſtion my Rulers commandment, which is like to be only perhaps in ſome grievous preſſure. If the Law be bad, my obedience yet and my example may do good, nor does the Magiſtrates abuſe of his office I hope take away my liberty to endure it if I pleaſe. The true ends more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over hapily of <hi>obedience,</hi> may be obtained, when the end of <hi>Ruling</hi> is neglected. Nay the <hi>common good</hi> may be promoted poſſibly, by my yeilding to a Law when the Law it ſelf does croſs it. And farther my diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience may do more hurt to the <hi>common
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39038:47"/>good</hi> then the obeying that hurtfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand would do. So farre am I from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging any from <hi>obedience</hi> to human Laws (as a thing generally good and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiall) when I would keep the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence free, and not have it burdened with ſin for every want of their performance. I ſee indeed by this and other learned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, what an immagination they have got, that if I reſolve the queſtion whether I am in Conſcience obliged to obey ſuch a Law, by my private judging of the thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded whether it be agreeable or not to the <hi>common good</hi> I do <hi>uſurpe the place of the Ruler and make myſelf only my own Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,</hi> as they are apt to ſpeak. But this is a miſtake, for beſides that when I judge of the thing commanded by its Rule, this judgement of mine is not the <hi>maker</hi> of my duty but the <hi>diſcerner</hi> of it, and ſo I do not become any Law-giver to my ſelf in the buſineſs: I diſtinguiſh the <hi>obligation of a human Law,</hi> and the <hi>obligation of Conſcience (formaliter. &amp; ſimpliciter</hi>) by that Law. If I reſolved the whole obligation of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Laws into this Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Law by it, ſo that I held it muſt never be obeyed on other reaſons,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39038:47"/>or that if I were puniſhed for not obeying, I was not bound to ſubmit, then did I offer injury indeed to my Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er and uſurped his Government. But if I reſolve only the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of my Conſcience by that Law</hi> into this rule, and my judgement of it accordingly, I uſurpe no power of the Magiſtrates, which I leave him ſtill over the <hi>exterior man,</hi> but I keep God only as I ought in his own feat of the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And verily if the Conſcience of man be concerned in every human law, I would fain know, how any of our great Clerks can ſay that human laws bind not in the caſe of intollerable griveance. If God does command me to do the thing, it is not any griveance of minde can excuſe me, but if it be man indeed commands it only and not God, the griveance will be reaſon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for me to call it in queſtion, and to avoid it if I may; but the reaſon of my non-obedience, muſt not have this founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it is my grievance, or that I cannot endure it, but that <hi>conſideratis conſiderandis,</hi> I am not obliged to it in Conſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:39038:48"/>
               <head>CAP. VII.</head>
               <p>THus far his exceptions are but <hi>words,</hi> let us paſs now to his <hi>reaſons</hi> againſt my anſwer.</p>
               <p>His firſt reaſon is, <hi>It is no eaſy thing to judge what is beſt for the Peoples good, Kings themſelves find it neceſſary to have their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cets to adviſe about it.</hi> To judge what is <hi>beſt</hi> for the Peoples good is indeed a high mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. To judge only whether a thing be for the common good or not, is another matter. The judgement of every one is free, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body may judge of any thing as he is able, and as he will. The Cock may paſs his judgement on the Pearl he ſcraped up. That which comes to carry any ſtreſs upon judging, is the conſideration of the effect that depends upon that judgement. The judging of a thing which a Man himſelf hath to do, hath this effect depending on it, the doing his duty, every one is to judge
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39038:48"/>of all thoſe things and circumſtances which belong to his own acts, whether or no they be agreeable to Gods will, that he may do as he ought; and the rule of this will in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticals, I have declared. There is the act now of the Magiſtrate, and the act of the Subject. There is a great difference of the concern or moment that lies on a judgement of the ſame thing when the act of the one depends upon it, and when there depends upon it the act only of the other. The act of the Magiſtrate is to make the law, and ſee it executed; the act of the People is to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it. By this firſt reaſon of his againſt my anſwer, do I ſee good reaſon for it, and the ſufficiency of it. The Magiſtrate judges whether a thing be for the common good, or according to our ſupream rule in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his paſſing it into a law, and then to cauſe it to be executed. The People and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular perſon does judge, whether the thing commanded be for the common good, in reference only to the obligation of their Conſciences to obedience. Upon the judgement of the Magiſtrate, there does depend an effect of univerſal concernment, that is the obligation of a whole Nation to live according to the Law he makes, upon
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:39038:49"/>the judgdement of each particular when the law is made, there depends no concern but a mans own, and that reſpecting his inward man only. Now its certain that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate in regard of ſuch an effect as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon his judgement, hath need indeed of the greateſt wiſdome, and the ableſt Councel, and he cannot be too cautions in his proceeding, ſeeing if he be miſtaken, and the Conſciences of the Subjects be not obliged by ſuch a law, yet are their perſons liable to be compelled and they muſt not reſiſt, which may prove a vaſt inconvenience, and to be avoided only by a right infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation at firſt about the matter. But as for a private perſon who judges not what is <hi>beſt</hi> for the peoples good (as he ſpeaks right in regard to the Magiſtrate) but onely judges of the thing commanded whether it be agreeable or not to the will of God, or the rule of his (which he hath given to the world about Politicals, if they forget not to minde it, to wit) that it be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneral for their good, the effect which (I have ſaid) does attend ſuch a judgement, is of that nature onely as requires no greater under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding or diſcretion, then every man hath for himſelf to act by in all the reſt of his life
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:39038:49"/>and converſation. He judges here accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Rule in theſe things, as he doth in other of his actions according to the word whether he be bound or not bound in Conſcience to them. And God requires of him to judge and act but according to his talent in all buſineſs whatſoever. He will acknowledge the outward man to be bound, and in a matter of his ſoul which concerns no body but him, or the inward obligation of his Conſcience, you muſt leave him to God and his own Judgement.</p>
               <p>His next reaſon is, <hi>That when Men know what is conducing to their good, they are not apt to do it without a Law.</hi> And what does this prove or contradict? It proves it good therefore that the people have a Law-giver or Governor, and that he ſhould be wiſer and better then they, as <hi>Plato</hi> may urge it: But does it follow they may not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judge, whether the thing commanded be for their good; Surely this will be a good reaſon why the people ſhould judge of it. For if the good they conceive in it, is the reaſon they admit to have any Law, and the argument to preſs them to obey it, then muſt they judge of that good, and whether it be conducive to that good or
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:39038:50"/>not. In the mean while the difference of the reaſon and ends, (which is diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> judging of a thing to be for the common good or not, and the peoples does ſufficiently declare the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and vanity of ſuch ſpeeches, as this Man hath ſeveral of. <hi>He that makes every Man judge of what is for the peoples good, takes away the principal power of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</hi> And why ſo? as if it were an act of power, and that uſurped for any but the Prince to have a judgement of diſcretion over his civil actions. Again, <hi>if the people be able to judge of that there is no need of any Law or Law-giver.</hi> As if when men knew their duty they needed no Magiſtrate to make them do it, and that while himſelf too is telling us the need of Laws, <hi>becauſe men a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e not like to prefer the publick good though they comprehend it, before that of their own particular perſons.</hi> I cannot I perceive, be throughly intent to anſwer what is inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, but the ſubſtance in the main of theſe two reaſons comes to this, that every man is not able to bring the thing commanded by the Magiſtrate to the rule, ſo as to judge whether it be for the common good or not, and therefore they muſt act only upon
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:39038:50"/>the judgement of the Law-giver, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently be no reaſonable agents, in their <hi>Political obedience.</hi> For ſatisfaction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this, Let us conceive the Magiſtrate commanding ſomething <hi>moral</hi> or <hi>Religious,</hi> there are no <hi>Proteſtants</hi> but do hold that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man for himſelf muſt bring here what is commanded to the rule of the moral Law and Scripture, and according as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf believes it conſonant or not to the rule he judges it, ſo is he bound to obey it or not to to obey it. Now let any man who hath but the heart to think and ſpeak with integrity, conſider whether a rude and illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate man that never could read a word in the Bible, be more able to judge whether a thing commanded by the Magiſtrate be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable or not to the word of God; or whether it be conducive or not to the common good? ſuppoſe the Waggoner as unlearned as any man, I will ask whether ſuch a man be not more able to judge of the Law concerning Waggons, that is whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good for the high wayes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently whether he had beſt or not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the act, then to judge whether the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or whether whatſoever is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:39038:51"/>in the whole Book of Common Prayer with the Rites and Ceremonies, be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able or not to the Scriptures of the old and New Teſtament? I ſuppoſe there is no man will have the hardi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe to oppoſe ſuch a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt conviction. And if in regard to his practice, this man and every other that uſes the Common-prayer muſt judge as well as he can of the lawfulneſs of it, or elſe he cannot act in faith: and ſo likewiſe of all thoſe doctrines or practiſes he yields unto them, then will there I hope be no ſtumbling block left here upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I do advance therefore and reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this one argument, if the incapacity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitneſs, or little ability that ſome men have to judge of what is required by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, whether it be agreeable or no to the common good, be a reaſon ſufficient for the denying to the ſubject ſuch a judgement: then muſt the leſſer ability of ſuch to judge whether that which is required be agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the word of God, be a reaſon ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to diſcharge them from judging of it by the word. But the conſequent is falſe, and therefore the antecedent. By the way, obſerve, if any man diſtinguiſh between judging of a <hi>Law</hi> whether it be for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:39038:51"/>good: and judging of the <hi>thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> by a law, or rather of a <hi>mans own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thing commanded,</hi> whether it be for the publick good or not, I am to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the laſt, when I ſay the Magiſtrate judges of the thing in reference to his paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it into a law and we judge of it ſo paſſed in reference to our obedience or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation by it.</p>
               <p>His third reaſon is the ſame with the firſt. <hi>The people are ſo far from being able to judge, that the wiſeſt Princes find it diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult,</hi> only we have more words for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement; which conſiſt partly in a grave kind of diſcourſe from a paſſage of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Bramhall,</hi> of the ſeverall things and circumſtances that the Law-giver is to weigh in his making of a law, which the people cannot conſider and attend unto: and then in an idle deſcant upon this, that it is not fit therefore that <hi>laws ſhould be ſuſpended till the ſubjects be agreed they are for their good,</hi> with the like words, as if there were any indeed ever dream'd that a Law-giver, who is with us the Parliament, could not make a law untill they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted the people firſt, whether they all of them judged the matter ſuch, that if it
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:39038:52"/>were paſſed into a law, they ſhould be bound in Conſcience to the performance, and before they had an affirmative anſwer from them (who muſt be made loath too to be ſatisfied about it) they could paſs no act or ſtatute of the Realm. This is the ſenſe in which this man let his pen run here, and then concludes. <hi>The Prince is in an ill caſe who hath ſuch ſubjects, and he is not in very good, whoſe Divines begin to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill ſuch doctrine into them</hi> If there be any thing in thoſe <hi>more words</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> reaſon that ſeems of moment, it is already anſwered I count by diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the part of the Law-giver, the ſubject, whoſe judgement of a thing commanded in a law already paſſed, for the ſatisfiy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf whether he be obliged in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to the doing, can by no means pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice the act of the Law-giver in the paſſing the law as is manifeſt, nor does it <hi>throw it down</hi> being paſſed. For this is a miſtake in this perſon very palpable, as if a human law could not be of force un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a mans Conſcience be obliged by it. I obſerved this in him before where he ſaid, <hi>Laws while they do oblige tye the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and that the cauſe of his error was
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:39038:52"/>the want of preſent knowledge to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between <hi>Political</hi> and <hi>morall</hi> obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. The obligation which is on the Conſcience is <hi>morall</hi> and can be no other, and paſſes on it I have ſaid from Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our generall duty: but the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation which is <hi>Political</hi> belongs to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man and may ſtand good when the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> ceaſes, and for as much as this obligation of the outward man it ſelf does ſo ariſe from the commandment of God for ſubjection, and that we ſhould not reſiſt, it may appear to the impartial that will conſider aright of what is ſaid, that the queſtion or ſingle point between this man and I concerning the obligation of human Laws, in reference only to the conſcience, is really and in good earneſt very little or not at all material to the Magiſtrate, or the civill Government, which way ſoever it is determined. And when there are ſo many learned men of divers ſorts who exerciſe their liberty in maintaining the opinion of either extream without controle or prejudice to the world, its a thing hardly becomming either a <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate minde,</hi> or <hi>modeſt Learning,</hi> or that I ſhould have moſt expected from this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour a <hi>free Theology,</hi> to expreſs himſelf in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:39038:53"/>this manner, as if a man could not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the finding out a middle way that is ſo needfull in ſuch a controverſie but he muſt be adjudged one that is broaching of ſomething againſt the <hi>State,</hi> and deſerved correction.</p>
               <p>His fourth reaſon is, <hi>Grant the ſubjects ſuch a power</hi> (that is, a power only of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their own civill acts) <hi>and in a little time no law ſhall be obſerved.</hi> He proceeds, Taxes will not be paid. He goes on. There will be Inſurrections and Rebellion. Upon this, he brings in certain narrations, of the Subſidy of Head money in <hi>Richard</hi> the Seconds time and what followed; of the aid granted to <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh in his third year and the Northern Rebellion; then of a ſubſidy in his thirteenth year when the <hi>Corniſh-men</hi> took up arms, then of the caſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight about Aliens, and of one <hi>John Lincoln</hi> a Broaker that was hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. See more in a certain <hi>dialogue between a Couceellor of ſtate, and a Juſtice,</hi> he has in his ſtudy; for this it is for the man to light on a new book, he muſt by all means be tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us of what he was reading laſt. And thus had we at the begining of theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers from the tenth argument of <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:39038:53"/>againſt Image worſhip, the relation of the <hi>Iconomachi</hi> and what befell them in the time of <hi>Leo Iſaurus;</hi> in the time of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Copronomus;</hi> in the time of the <hi>horrible cold and freezing of the</hi> Pontick <hi>Sea,</hi> the <hi>drought</hi> after, and the <hi>death</hi> of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, The man hath a ſtrange fruitful application. This brings to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance an advice once I received from an ingenious and prudent Woman, who ſeeing me over ingaged in diſpute ſometimes with an Anabaptiſt, who was a man of much talk and being not willing I ſhould be ſo much concerned: you muſt not ſays ſhe, argue with theſe men in the way you do; you lay down the ſubject, and ſpeak upon that, and then think to hold them to it, and are moved when they ſpeak from the point, and ſo are confounded; but you ſhould (ſayes ſhe) give them leave to ſpeak ſo long until you can lay hold on ſomething that they ſay, and whatſoever it is, you muſt ſpeak of that; and by this means while you take them up ſtill upon their laſt words, whether it be to the point or not, you will never want matter no more then they do, and by the uſe of their own weapon may deal with them. I muſt profeſs if this man who hath
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39038:54"/>ſo apt an expreſſion, do come to get this knack of it, as he appears to have in theſe <hi>continuations</hi> and <hi>apendix,</hi> he may continue his continuations while he lives, and I know no body able to diſpute with him, unleſs I could light on the fellow that would preach with any body, but it ſhould be (he ſaid) in a <hi>Negative</hi> way, <hi>And</hi> Peter <hi>went to</hi> Antioch. He went not to be drunk, here he ſpeaks of drunkenneſs, gluttony, and all manner of exceſs. He went not to lye with women, there he ſpeaks of fornication, and unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and all other deadly ſin. But he went to preach, there he ſpeaks of the Scriptures from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the <hi>Revelation,</hi> of the Fathers the Schoolemen, the Councels, and all the books that ever he read to this day.</p>
               <p>For the reaſon it ſelf without its appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, I have I account prevented it in the ſtate of my opinion. The ſtate alone of what I have ſaid, will wipe off any ſuch miſtaken conſequence, which he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly bring upon it. It is one queſtion whether we are to obſerve a law: &amp; another whether we are bound in Conſcience to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. The queſtion between us in the bottom of the point is not concerning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obſervation: but the inward obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:39038:54"/>of Conſciences. And the truth is as I was ſaying at the cloſe of the other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that this buſineſs does not really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Magiſtrate, or the Common-wealth directly at all (though indirectly and <hi>ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequenti</hi> any thing may concern any body) for what is it to the Magiſtrate or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, ſo long as he can enforce the thing to be done if he will, whether a man does do it out of Conſcience, or out of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only: out of fear of God, or fear of the law, or his ſword. The Magiſtrate cannot take any cognizance out of what principle a man acts; the judgement is not within his jurisdiction, and if a man doth not act out of Conſcience, he cannot make him. It is ſufficient, ſo long as a man acknowledges his authority from God, that he muſt therefore be ſubject and muſt not reſiſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently if in good earneſt he ſtand upon it, and will have obedience from him, let it be in any thing but ſin, there is no help for him that is, he may not help himſelf by reſiſtance) but he muſt yield to it, whether he will or no. This is that which ſecures government, and Governors. Let every man be held bound in Conſcience but thus far, and as for the reſt, it is a matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:39038:55"/>each ones own ſoul only and his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate peace, and it will become thoſe that are prudent to be very tender what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in the buſineſs.</p>
               <p>It is true this reverend Perſon thought I believe he had ſpoken well in his ſaying, that <hi>it is hard to write any thing more inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and dangerous</hi> then that I have: but if a man ſhould write any word againſt <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> to Magiſtracy, or his own preſent Magiſtrate, or that it were lawful to reſiſt if the Magiſtrate ſhould impoſe any law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common good (when yet it is not ſin, I account many times not to <hi>obey</hi> it, and eſcape if we can without reſiſtance), this let me tell him were dangerous (I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay <hi>more dangerous</hi> becauſe the other is not dangerous,) that the man may receive ſome ſhame and conviction for his own being ſo inconſiderate in his cenſure of what he underſtood no better. This De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bater ſhall not have I will warrant him, a breath or Title of this nature from me. Nay if a law be good I mean politically good (and a law is politically good where it is for the common good,) I am ready to believe and hold it is obliging, obliging to the Conſcience, not only that we muſt obey
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:39038:55"/>rather then reſiſt (which we muſt do if the thing be politically evil, unleſs we count ſuffering to be better) but if we could eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape with man, we muſt yet do it, I count leaſt we offend God, if a law be not poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically good, I ſay we muſt not reſiſt for all that, and upon that account rather then ſuffer we are lyable to obedience. And what is there now, or what reaſon is there that any ſhould deſire more. Let us here our man of Proverbs. A <hi>man muſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt (ſayes our Caſuiſt) that is expreſs, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then reſiſt he muſt ſuffer, but this is to ſteal a gooſe, and ſtick a feather;</hi> I thank him firſt for this, that he hath not left out this paſſage wholly in this place, leaſt his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der elſe might have thought me indeed ſome dangerous perſon, whereas theſe words have acquitted me; and I anſwer, that this <hi>Gooſe</hi> he ſpeaks of my ſtealing, is the thing ought to be <hi>ſtolen</hi> or removed, and that which he makes <hi>ſo light of,</hi> is to be brought in the Room of it, to wit, this man is of opinion that human laws even all laws indefinitely bind the Conſcience, ſo that a man muſt ſin if he break any of them, This is his Gooſe, that is, his fooliſh opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, an opinion intollerable: and inſtead
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:39038:56"/>of this, that which I would bring in is, that though we conceive there be ſome laws, which if a man ſometimes obſerves not, he is not to charge himſelf with ſin, yet if he be compelled by the lawful Magiſtrate, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then reſiſt he muſt ſuffer, and rather then ſuffer obey. <hi>But why muſt he</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>when he is already perſwaded that he need not unleſs he be forced?</hi> this is ſtrange! where is this Debaters reaſon! I ſay he muſt, though he ſhould not ſin elſe by neglect, <hi>becauſe</hi> he is forced, and cannot help it, but for avoiding of ſuffering, he does it. <hi>But wrath</hi> or ſuffering <hi>is not to be feared when the multitude is agreed not to be injured.</hi> I anſwer here is the want of the diſtinction which this author would not take from me, between the authority which is in the Magiſtrates Perſon, and that of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. The one is from God immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the other mediately by vertue of the things commanded being for the common good, and ſo particulars of that generall morall duty which is required of God. Some may uſe other words to expreſs this diſtinction by the Magiſtrates <hi>authority</hi> it ſelf, and the <hi>exerciſe of it</hi> in his commands or laws: but this muſt be known that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:39038:56"/>we muſt here to the ſame ſenſe I intend, and be very careful too of the diſtinction or we ſhall be loſt. If the multitude be agreed not to do a thing that is ill, it is well I take it, and as they ought, it was manifeſtly <hi>Jonathans</hi> caſe. But if they agree together not to ſuffer, if the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate will enforce the thing, let there be but the leaſt Officer will act in it, then they reſiſt, and ſin againſt God, and it is not juſtify able upon any terms, ſuppoſe a whole army and but two men in it will ſtand by the Prince, he may. I muſt affirm to ſpeak ſtrictly on the point of Conſcience, by theſe two men alone, puniſh a whole army for any thing they refuſe to do, and they muſt bear it, and cannot help themſelves, but with ſin which they muſt not do. <hi>For he that reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and receiveth to himſelf damnation.</hi> We know the caſe under <hi>Maximinian,</hi> when a whole legion of Chriſtians were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſacrifice, and they choſe rather to ſuffer decimation twice over, being exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted man by man, rather then defend themſelves while their lives were at ſtake, and the ſword was in their hands. Such a Conſcience ought we to have of our <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:39038:57"/>(and ſo much does the concern of government and the whole World lye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it,) when of <hi>obedience</hi> as to ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar commands we need to have none. In ſhort there lyes no obligation upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſometimes <hi>to obey,</hi> but there does alwayes <hi>not to reſiſt,</hi> and that both ſerves the Magiſtrate turn, and ſuffices when he pleaſes to have a civil thing done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:39038:57"/>
               <head>CAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>I will not yet leave his laſt reaſon, ſeeing he layes ſo much ſtreſs on it, and his ſtrength of all comes to this. I do not take here his very words, but matter which he may expreſs as he will otherwiſe. <hi>The People muſt not be allowed to judge of their own actions, which are commanded by the Magiſtrate about civil things, becauſe they will be ſwayed by their own intereſts, and judge thoſe Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the publick good which are not for their private profit: by which means unleſs they be taught and hold that all Laws indefinitely do bind their Conſciences, they will notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Magiſtrates power, abſolve themſelves from what they pleaſe, no Laws will be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and all Government come to the ground,</hi> Unto this as his ſubſtance, beſides my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer I have already given, I ſhall crave leave to offer a few conſiderations.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, this is certainly a ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w apprehenſion, which muſt ſuffer a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction from the conſtant experience of the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:39038:58"/>world. For how is the world governed? there is not one of a hundred that obſerves the Laws out of Conſcience; if they did, then muſt they for ought I know be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the Statutes and read them as their bibles, which one of a thouſand never do. But men underſtand, it they do ſuch or ſuch things, they are l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able to be ſued, or to be bound to the Seſſions or the like, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the danger of the Law, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. Now it is a fooliſh thing to ſay the Laws will not be obſerved, or the world will not be governed, unleſs by another means then that by which it <hi>is</hi> governed, and the Law <hi>are</hi> obſerved. Our Nations and Heathen Nations, and thoſe Nations which never had the fear of God to believe a judgement to come, have been kept under the obſervation of the Laws of their Country by theſe means.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place, this is not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt univerſal experience, but it confronts the very inſtitution of God, the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Magiſtracy, God hath made the Magiſtrate his Miniſter, and put the ſword into his hand, for the ordering and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Societies, and Common wealths, and if this indeed will not ſerve that purpoſe, then
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:39038:58"/>you render his inſtitution inſufficient, and make his <hi>Miniſter</hi> to <hi>bear</hi> the <hi>ſword in vain.</hi> The Law (ſayes the Apoſtle) is not made for the righteous, but the diſobedient and unrighteous. If all were righteous and would of themſelves make Conſcience of doing what they ſhould do, there would be no need of Magiſtrate or Law: but when the Law and Magiſtrate is appointed for this end: to bring the refractory to order, and thoſe that make no Conſcience of what they do to be ruled, how fond muſt the imagination be which conceits, unleſs men do firſt beleive themſelves bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to obey, they will not obſerve the Laws?</p>
               <p>In the third place, if it be for ſome perſons particular intereſt to break the Laws, it will be the concern of others that they be forced to keep them if they be indeed for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good: &amp; ſo ſhall they joyn with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate in his cauſing the execution of them. This indeed is that which upholds all Laws that are good. The publick intereſt being greater then the private does uphold them. Whereas if a Law be not really for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, this is one certain reaſon at the bottom of its invalidity, and decay, becauſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:39038:59"/>it hath not root enough, upon the publick utility, to maintain it ſelf againſt particular enchroachments. If a <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> come within five miles of a Corporation there is no body hurt by it, and no body like to be concerned at it, were this a thing truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the publick good, then muſt the publick be diſadvantaged in their breach of that Law; and if the publick, then muſt ſome more eminently, and thoſe ſhould be as much concerned, that they obey as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to avoid the obſervation. By the way, when the advantage for the publick does not countervaile and exceed the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate loſs or dammage that particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall ſuffer by a Law, ſuch a Law I take to be unjuſt, or at leaſt Politically evil, and binds not the Conſcience. However that which I here affirm is, that whether men make a Conſcience of a Law or not, if the Law be good: the publick advantage will prevail (when the Magiſtrate is minded) or cauſe it to be obſerved.</p>
               <p>In the fourth place, it is a thing very <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politick</hi> to offer to the world any principle upon which it ſhould be governed, which is other then that which does govern it. If the world be governed by the Magiſtrates
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:39038:59"/>ſword, and the Conſcience only that we muſt not rebell, and is governed as well as ever it is like to be governed: it is but an unhinging the world to pretend they muſt receive this principle, <hi>that human laws bind the Conſcience; or elſe there will be no need to obey, ſeeing the People may joyn and chuſe not to be forced</hi> as he ſpeaks. It is a ſaying, if a Horſe knew his ſtrength, what might he not do? he would not let man ride him and uſe him as he does. If the world knew their ſtrength, that the Magiſtrate indeed could not puniſh them whatſoever they did, unleſs they joyned with him one againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, when there is juſt cauſe for it, they might ſhake off every yoke: but as the whole body of the People cannot be made to know this, ſo as at once to agree upon it, any more then the Horſe can, though every particular man does know it: ſo were it an utterly ruinous thing to ſpeak of it if they could. It is true if the people did agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether (which agreement is their ſtrength, and they cannot know one anothers preſent minds all) that they would not be forced, they might chooſe: but then when they made no Conſcience to <hi>reſiſt,</hi> how ſhould this man think upon his principle, that they
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:39038:60"/>would make ſuch Conſcience to obey.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, it does ſeem to me a pernicious thing to the ſouls of pious and tender Chriſtians, to lay any ſuch load up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Conſcience which is more then it can bear. I ſay there is no temptation hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more dangerous to the undoing of a ſoul, then to preſs it upon ſuch things as goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it, and over ſets it. If a man does believe he is bound to make Conſcience of every command of his ſuperiour and Law of the Realm or elſe he doth ſin, it is enough to make him caſt off all the Laws, and when his duty is made ſo grevious to him, that it ſeems impoſſible for him but to live in ſin, to be ready for <hi>reſiſtance</hi> next, and then all Magiſtracy is gon. The way to have ſome Laws obeyed out of Conſcience, is to take off its obligation from others; and if a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate indeed might chooſe whether his Subjects Conſciences ſhould be bound by all his Laws or not, there is good reaſon for him to be content that the matter ſhould be as it is. They are bound in Conſcience not to reſiſt, and he knows not his own ſtrength if he deſire any more: although when a Law is for the common good, then is there Gods command alſo which takes
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:39038:60"/>place. There is one thing I cannot but add, which might make another conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what if a deſpotical Prince was ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as reſolving to be damned himſelf to ſeek the damnation of all his people, and ſhould thereupon make ſo many Laws, and about ſuch trivial things on purpoſe, that none of his Subjects might regard to keep them, but live and die in the wilful breach of them: I pray let this Debater tell me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally whether according to his opinion it does not lye in the power of ſuch a Divel as this is, to carry a whole Nation to Hell with him.</p>
               <p>In the ſixth place, let us ſuppoſe the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men were bound indefinitely to all Laws, does this Author think really that the belief of this would make the world to obſerve them, and ſo maintain Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more then the Magiſtrates ſword? I doubt me he is here more wide: we ſee too well that when the worldly or carnal inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of men is concerned, what little regard Conſcience has. It were happy indeed for the Earth if the fear of God Almighty did but prevail more with the Generality then the fear of a ſuite at Law, or a Penalty of twenty ſhillings. If intereſt will prevail
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:39038:61"/>with a man, to judge a thing commanded him to be againſt the common good, when it is for it, the ſame intereſt of his it is like with ſuch a man would prevaile ſtill upon him not to obſerve the Law, though he were bound in Conſcience to it.</p>
               <p>In the ſeventh place, then thoſe few ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perſons that would obſerve a Law if they thought themſelves bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to it, not withſtanding their private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt be againſt it, will likewiſe make the like Conſcience in their judging of a Law, ſo as not to be byaſſed by their particular concernment to think otherwiſe of it, then does comport with the publick advantage. And this in effect will come to the ſame iſſue.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place. I will offer you one preſident to pinne the basket. It pleaſed God in the late times that this caſe became Dr. <hi>Saunderſons</hi> own caſe. The Act of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformity bound the Miniſter to read Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer. This Law the Dr. acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges to be of force, for all the Times; but if he obſerves the Law he muſt looſe his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. Upon this he conſiders of the Act, and when he looks on the <hi>immediate particular</hi> end of it, he can find nothing but that their remains obliged to it. He then looks on the <hi>general</hi> and <hi>ultimate</hi> end, and that he conceives
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:39038:61"/>right to be the publick good, wch is intended or is to be ſuppoſed to be intended in all laws. Upon this end he comes to the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whether all circumſtances being weighed, it be conducive for the common good for him to obſerve this Law or not: and being in the reſult fully perſwaded in his own mind that the benefit to the publick could no wayes countervail his particular loſs and ſuffering he concludes it lawful by the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of that Law to retain his living. There is a ſober perſon having read my Caſe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me a Manuſcript of the Doctors (but would not let me write any thing out of it) for the confirmation of my judgement. I cannot relate either the whole matter or words of it, but theſe two things I affirm for truth in it. That be comes off upon the conſideration of the general end of the Law, the publick benefit: and judges him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf whether his obſerving that Law were conducive to that end in reference to the determining his own practice. And here I have (I account) my full weight for my ſelf, and think I had beſt to fetch the poor man before alſo, who finding no ſufficient relief from this Authour about his Cottage, may meet with it from this inſtance to his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:39038:62"/>ſatisfaction, and it will come to this, whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeems a little more then I have yet quite ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that not only when a Law is politically <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vil, but when it is good in regard of its ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral obſervation, yet if a man be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fully in his Conſcience upon ſuch du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conſiderations and cautions as he ought to take, that his particular keeping of it under the preſent circumſtances he lyes, is not ſo much for the common good really as his not keeping of it is (which I will take to be plainly this poor mans caſe inſtanced, who if he holds not his houſe muſt with his Family preſently fall on the Pariſh), he is not to charge his ſoul with ſin for his wholeſome breach of it. After this I will yet ſubjoyn a little more in reference alſo to ſome others. When the Apoſtle gives us this precept, <hi>obey thoſe that have the rule ovér you,</hi> though there be no words added by way of exception, it is to be ſuppoſed the things they command are for our edification, this being a condition neceſſarily implyed to all rightful obedience, that the Ruler hath authority in what he injoynes. But the Miniſter hath authority only for mens edification, and hath none in things againſt their ſpiritual good, <hi>according to our authority</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:39038:62"/>(ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>for edification, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> The Caſe is the ſame with the Magiſtrate. His commands that have au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority muſt be to our <hi>civil</hi> good. It is a miſtake therefore (how ingenious and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſoever it may ſeem in ſome that ſay, the people have liberty to judge indeed, whether a thing commanded be <hi>lawful,</hi> but not at all whether it be <hi>convenient.</hi> That by all means they count it to be denyed, as if the allowing any ſuch thing would preſently (as this author fancies too) ſubvert all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I heſe Perſons I perceive therefore diſtinguiſh not between judging what is ſit for the general, or univerſality, which judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment indeed is proper to the ſupream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate: and judging what is fit for a mans ſelf only to doe. <hi>All things are lawful for our</hi> (ſayes the apoſtle) <hi>But all things are not expedient.</hi> I <hi>will not be brought under the power of any.</hi> a Chriſtian judges for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of both theſe; of the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> and of the <hi>expedience</hi> of his own actions. If this be not granted then muſt he be brought <hi>under the power</hi> of indifferent things, which he ought not to be: and then does he <hi>ſubmit</hi> himſelf unto the <hi>Ordinance of man</hi> or the <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Creature</hi> as <hi>his</hi> ſervant and not as <hi>free</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:39038:63"/>and <hi>as the Servant of God.</hi> Again theſe perſons have not yet conſidered what I have been telling ſtill in theſe papers, that this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is aſſumed of us in reference only to the Conſcience or to our obligation <hi>in for interiori;</hi> and that while the outward man i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtill acknowledged to be <hi>bound,</hi> there is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> danger at all to Government in the matter On the contrary ſide there is this intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſnare, or evil conſequence does follow on the denyal hereof, that every time any human Law (the matter whereof is not for bidden of God) is not obſerved, the ſubject muſt ſin, and conſequently if he live and dyes knowingly and wilfully, in his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect he muſt be damned, I will yet propoſe therefore one or two inſtances. There is a Statute in <hi>Henry</hi> the eights time (if I miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take not) which remains unrepealed, that no man ſhall brew with Hopps. I do ask hereupon whether there be any Brewer in this Nation knowing of this, that can be ſaved? I do not find my Debator can anſwer me this queſtion; and I do not doubt but there are many Brewers that are honeſt men and <hi>good Chriſtians,</hi> as well as I believe he is. If you will ſay that this Law now is antiquated through diſuſe; I will ask then
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:39038:63"/>what think you of thoſe Brewers that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed it at firſt? was they all damned ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily who willfully brought it into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe? the Caſe is a frequent Caſe as to all the like Laws, and you muſt come at length to this, that thoſe who obſerved not this Law at firſt did judge it was not good for the Nation, or not fit to be kept: and upon that judgement are to be juſtified. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows then both that a Law againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good binds not the Conſcience: and that every man for himſelf may judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo or no in reference to his own acting. Another inſtance ſhall be this, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Father or a Maſter lays ſome ſtrict charge on his Son or Servant to lay out a Thouſand pounds on a Commodity which is more perhaps (but for his Credit) then he is worth by half. This Son or Servant in going to do it, bears of the growing or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of this Commodity by great quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in ſome parts of the Kingdome, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own diſcretion alone and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of what may fall our, forbears, his Father or Maſter perhaps now at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is grievouſly chaſed: but within few days the price of the Commodity falls half, and then he ſees that if he had been obeyed
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:39038:64"/>he had been undone. From hence doe there appear not only the neceſſity, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, of allowing a judgement of diſcretion unto Perſons of capacity, under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of their Superiours; and that I ſay not meerly to judge whether the thing commanded be lawful or unlawful in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference unto God whereof there is no queſtion: but whether it be convenient or inconvenient to that end or outward good which by that command is deſigned. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears alſo from both theſe inſtances, that the commands of men do not by vertue of the fifth Commandement it ſelf bind the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>immediately</hi> and <hi>abſolutely,</hi> but medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately and <hi>ex hypotheſi,</hi> to wit upon ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thoſe commands are good, <hi>human laws</hi> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> will have it <hi>bind the Conſcience di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and properly.</hi> I do not love to diſpute about terms, but if any think he intends <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately,</hi> he is out, for they do bind only by the intervention of Gods will, he argues, the authority of the Magiſtrate is Gods au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. I anſwer the authority which is in the perſon of the Magiſtrate as Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is Gods authority, and binds directly and immediatly to <hi>ſubjection:</hi> but the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> of the Magiſtrate have not Gods au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:39038:64"/>unleſs the things commanded be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to his will, and then it is by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention of his will, I ſay, that the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is bound to obedience. A third thing appears that the Conſcience of man is not bound by vertue of Gods authority unto <hi>every</hi> command of our Superiors though the thing commanded be in a matter ſometimes which of it ſelf or its own Nature, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different becauſe the conſideration then of the external commodity, or diſcommodity only, could not juſtifie the breaker of any of them. If as ſoon as a Father or Maſter had forbidden any thing, the Commandment of God took place <hi>immediatly,</hi> and he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is to be reckoned to forbid it too, this Son or Servant might not break ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand though he did gain a thouſand pounds, or though either that Maſter or Father ſhould be undone by it There be ſeveral examples might be fech't from Hiſtories of great <hi>Commanders</hi> and <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> that to a chieve ſome great exploits have been forc't to leave the <hi>inſtructions</hi> of their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for which though at their return they have begged their pardon (out of form) as being obnoxious to the Law, yet have they had that Conſcience of their own fact to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:39038:65"/>them and toward God, as not only to be free from ſin, in that diſobedience, but to expect ſome ſignal reward for the ſervice of ſuch tranſgreſſions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus much for his grand exception, I muſt now look out for others, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſſage elſe that requires Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>At the firſt there comes to my view in General, the cavilling way which he uſes toward me, as if when a Man wanted a <hi>good anſwer,</hi> he ſhould ſhew an <hi>ill Spirit,</hi> which I would not believe in this Author. I perceive he pretends often that the Apologiſt doth wrong him and ſo accuſes him of <hi>falſifyings</hi> and <hi>impertinences,</hi> which are his frequent
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:39038:65"/>words: But in the mean while I wonder he ſhould not ſee how notoriouſly he is guilty of both theſe fine things himſelf. <hi>It would be no great matter</hi> (ſays he) <hi>if the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſt imitated not theſe men only in their phraſe, and not in their weak reaſonings,</hi> and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces an obſervation I have of providence in <hi>tranſitu,</hi> as if I argued ſomething from thence, which if he could tell what, he would confute no doubt, and he well might, wherefore it is manifeſt I lay that paſſage down and make no reaſoning at all upon it, neither do I imitate any bodies phraſe, nor tye my ſelf to any part, And if this then be not <hi>falſifying</hi> neither ſhall his four or five ſides after about Image worſhip, be any <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinency:</hi> nor his ſix or ſeven pages in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place about the Taxes and Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections there has been in this Nation: no though he ſhould tell you the whole Life and Death of <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> and <hi>Jack Straw,</hi> with a more perfect Narration yet of that Dr. <hi>Standiſh,</hi> unto whom <hi>John Lincoln</hi> the <hi>Broker came when he was to preach at the Spittle on a Monday in Eaſter week.</hi> This ſhould alſo be no impertinency, but a forceable confutation of whatſoever is ſaid by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologiſt or me. He may next tell us any
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:39038:66"/>other ſtory as well out of the Chronicles. Of <hi>Jack Cad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and his Cozen <hi>Mortimer.</hi> Of <hi>Lambert Simuel</hi> and the Lady <hi>Margret</hi> his Aunt. How might he have mauld us with the Relation of <hi>Perkin Warb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Plamm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck,</hi> and <hi>Robert Ket</hi> with his Oak of Reformation, and then kil'd us quite dead with an arrow our of <hi>Robin Hoods</hi> bow? In the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt there was the noble Earl <hi>Robin Hood,</hi> and one little <hi>John,</hi> and an hundred ſtout Fellows more, robbed the Paſſengers upon the High way. And what indeed is it that we may well think of ſuch a Roving faculty we ſee in this Authors laſt books, but that the Mans pen hath got a <hi>leoſeneſs,</hi> and that is the reaſon he hath ſo be ſpattered the poor Apologiſt, whoſe ill luck and my good one it was, that he came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and me. This is the reaſon that makes him come <hi>abroad</hi> ſo often, in a Debate, a <hi>continuation</hi> of that debate, a <hi>continuation</hi> of that continuation, an <hi>appendix</hi> to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuations continuation, and a <hi>Poſt-ſcript</hi> to that appendix to that continuation, of the continuation of the <hi>Friendly Debate. Nec dum fini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us Oreſtes.</hi> I muſt needs ſay here, I have been tempted to uſe ſome expreſſions that perhaps might be grateful to many who
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:39038:66"/>are willing to have a perſon (as they are apt to ſpeak) met with in his kind, but I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member there is a ſelf-denyal to be uſed in our writings as in our converſations, and there is an office of Love and honour we owe to worthy perſons; and when I may uſe ſuch expreſſions as theſe I think from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Elijah,</hi> I muſt uſe no bitterneſs from the command of the Apoſtle, nor any word from an offended mind from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our Saviour and Lord.</p>
               <p>The next thing which preſents it ſelf to my notice is a paſſage which hath a malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant aſpect on my opinion, or on what I have ſaid, yet ſhall be found but a friend to it. I am ſenſible now and then of a learing hint from this engaged man, I chooſe to be a little free with him, ſeeing he hath chalked out that way to me, but do reflect again on that word as having too aptly or truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the thing, whether I had beſt let it ſtand. By a learing paſſage I underſtand any ſuch as reflects any thing upon me, which ſeems to him to render me obnoxious, beſides the being ſlighted above what is juſt. Nevertheleſs when I perceive he ſpeaks out of ignorance, that is out of the want of a fuller underſtanding in this particular mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:39038:67"/>of what he reproves, I am ſuſtained with my own opinion and the integrity of it. Although too, while he conceits his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo ſuperior, it is all one for me, to taſt his Spirit. When I ſay ignorance, to wit hitherto, in reference to this point, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not this perſon to be an ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. No I hold him to be a learned Man of very much ability, and the leaſt of his ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency <hi>I</hi> take to be for diſpute. <hi>I</hi> compare not my ſelf with him. <hi>I</hi> know the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my houſhold ſtuff yet this have <hi>I,</hi> that when a particular point gets into my head, it coſts me more thoughts uſually then others will beſtow upon it, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought not in every thing <hi>I</hi> ſay, be ſo readily contemned. In the moſt points that ever I ſtudied I could arrive ordinarily but to this, that there is reaſon on both ſides. That to be dogmatical is not ſafe. I do ſometimes ſpeak for a thing out of <hi>courage,</hi> to bear it up againſt the ſtream, rather then out of pride. I have ſcarce ever come up to ſo much confidence in any point as I have in this in good earneſt, and if I ſhew it too much though i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be out of the ſimplicity of my heart, I could help it if I would, but that I think the world requires it, and the matter
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:39038:67"/>will bear it, for I am my ſelf a peice of duſt. The paſſage is this, <hi>The Caſuiſts principle if perſued will prove the very ſame with that in the perverſe meaning of it ſo much cryed up, when all our miſchiefs began, ſalus populi ſuprema lex<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the right underſtanding of which maxime I refer you to the laſt Lecture of Dr. Saunderſon. It</hi> is very much that this perſon ſhould ſee at firſt glimp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon what foundation all that I ſay does ſtand and that this foundation is made good by Dr. <hi>Saunderſon,</hi> and yet that he ſhould go to put ſuch a ſlur as this on it, without any good conſideration or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</p>
               <p>As for the maxime which <hi>in the words</hi> is fercht from <hi>Cicero de legibus,</hi> out of what o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Roman Law ſoever he had it, <hi>in the truth</hi> it is no leſs antient then Magiſtracy or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it ſelf, and ſhall ſtand ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>long as there is any in the World. There be ſome have abuſed the holy Goſpel and turned it into wantonneſs, but the abuſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is no cauſe ſufficient to throw off the Goſpel. No more is the abuſe of this maxime ſufficient reaſon to hinder any the patronage of it. You may as well lay aſide the Goſpel in Religion, as this truth out of Politicks, without which neither any ſociety
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:39038:68"/>or Common-wealth, or the World it ſelf could ſtand. I do hugely like the deſign of this Dr. in that Lecture which is the vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that Maxime, that every one may ſafely imbrace it, and I aſſent to all ſo far as I remember he hath ſaid of it; but yet I muſt needs ſay, I think not the Lecture moſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient of his Lectures, who appears rather as himſelf accounts, ſomething out of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtudy, when he is drawn upon it.</p>
               <p>That which he ſayes is no leſs truth then obvious, that under the word <hi>populus</hi> we muſt comprehend the ſupream Magiſtrate as well as the Subject. It is <hi>trite,</hi> that <hi>Plebs</hi> and <hi>Populus</hi> in Political Writers are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and this may be moſt convincing that in <hi>Ciceroes</hi> time (whoſe words theſe are) the Roman people was a Common-wealth, ſo that the ſupream Magiſtracy it ſelf lay in the body of the people, ſo far it is from any Juſtice or Right, that any ſhould make uſe of this maxime to ſuppreſs the cheif Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by it. The good of the people in their publick capacity is the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. A Common-wealth conſiſts in the order of ſuperiority and inferiority. The Common-wealths good then is the good of Magiſtrates and Subjects, the common
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:39038:68"/>intereſt of one is alſo the Intereſt of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There being no conſequence deduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble therefore from this maxime for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to riſe up againſt the King any more then againſt themſelves, or their own wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, There is one queſtion I think wanting in that Lecture of the Dr. whereof neither he (as the truth is) nor this man have yet caſt any right account, It is this, How comes it to paſs that when this maxime doth warrant the ſubject in not obeying ſome Laws which are made by the Magiſtrate, it will by no means warrant any ſubject to riſe againſt or reſiſt the Magiſtrate if he will execute them upon him? The anſwer to this will be like the invention of making the Egg ſtand an end, that is ſo apparent and eaſie, that you will wonder it ſhould not be ſeen already by every body. VVhen the common good then or the good of the community, is ſaid to be the ſupream Law, it muſt be underſtood moſt undoubtedly in reference to thoſe laws which are made for the community. Ex <hi>illis haec ſuprema lex eſto.</hi> If there be any one of ſuch conſequently does claſh with this, which is the cheif or ſuperior to them all, that is, if there be any law made which is not indeed for the common good, then is the ſubject manifeſtly diſcharged by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this maxime from any obligation to it, in the point of equity or conſcience. But
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:39038:69"/>it is as manifeſt likewiſe, that we are not to underſtand this maxime in reference to Gods Laws. To wit, The common good is the ſupream Law to all other Laws of the <hi>State,</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll human Laws, which are made to that end, the publick good of civil ſociety: but it is not ſupream to Gods Laws, or to any Law of God religious or moral which are made to another end, to wit the glorifying of God, not in order to our civil happineſs, but our everlaſting ſalvation. VVhen God ſays <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me,</hi> a Roman or a Greek might not ſay no it is ſon the good of our Country that many Gods be worſhipped, and the <hi>common good</hi> muſt take place of other Laws. For beſides that it is falſe to think it for the good of any ſtate, to have more then one God; The Law of the <hi>common good</hi> is to take place over the <hi>Common wealths</hi> Law, or is the <hi>ſupream</hi> Law, I ſay to all <hi>human</hi> Laws, but not to <hi>Gods</hi> Laws, which comes not under any ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuch <hi>good</hi> but do concern the <hi>ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of Mens ſouls. Now it is the Law or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God that Magiſtracy be ſet up, that we be in <hi>ſubjection</hi> to the <hi>powers that are,</hi> that is the preſent Magiſtrate that we have, and that we <hi>reſiſt not.</hi> This is no leſs his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:39038:69"/>then that we have no other Gods but him. If there be any then will argue we are not obleiged in Conſcience to <hi>obey a Law</hi> which is not for the common good upon the account of this maxime: Therefore we are not obleiged in Conſcience to <hi>ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Magiſtrate</hi> if he <hi>rule</hi> not for the <hi>common good</hi> upon account of the ſame, he is greatly miſtaken. Becauſe this maxime as we are to know, was Originally intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo is to be underſtood on neceſſity, in reference to the Laws of men, or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths Laws only, and not in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Commandments of God. Again, when a human Law paſſes for the good of the community, the common good being the ſupream rule and meaſure of all, every one judges and ought to judge (upon the pinch of the queſtion) whether the thing commanded be for the common good, that is, whether it be agreeable to the ſupream Law, and according as he judges and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves it to be or no, ſo is he obliged in Conſcience or not to it. But when a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate rules not as he ought, and ſo we are free as to his inordinate commands, there is no man may judge whether he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or the Government it ſelf be for the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:39038:70"/>good or no. You will ſay why? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the powers that be</hi> are <hi>of God,</hi> and <hi>his Ordinance,</hi> and whether the Ordinance of God be for our good or no, there is no mortal may queſtion or is to iudge. God hath himſelf declared this that he is <hi>the Miniſter of God for our good</hi> even <hi>Nero</hi> was, and no man may once offer to determine contrary to Gods declared word, or tell the Almighty he ſayes not truth. Conſequently when a Law ſometimes doth paſs that is not for the common good, and a man judging of it according to truth is not obliged in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>obedience,</hi> vet the Magiſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf being for our good (God having deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined ſo and mans judgement being confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his) even by this maxime it ſelf that the common good is the ſupream Law, he muſt be ſtill bound to <hi>ſubjection.</hi> And what now is become of this mans reproach which he hath laid to my charge with ſo much falſhood, and little judgement? as if Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> and he were for this maxime in the right ſenſe, and I was for it in the perverſe meaning, when it is plain that indeed neither he nor Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> (how worthy ſoever in their pacts otherwiſe) underſtood this maxim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the full import of it, ſeeing elſe he
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:39038:70"/>would have determined the main caſe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then I do.</p>
               <p>And this brings me to another paſſage of this Debater, which I was willing to reſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill now, both for the agreement of it here, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd for making a diſcovery of ſome of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uthours <hi>ſtrong reaſonings,</hi> who counts mine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>weak. It is reſolved by the Caſuiſt, that if the Magiſtrate command any thing for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hurt, there lies no obligation upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to obey, and they are made judges of what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s for their hurt. If then he require them not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o reſiſt and they find this is for their hurt, they are not bound in Conſcience not to reſiſt.</hi> Is not this very goodly? Does not the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhew us here indeed what a <hi>fathome</hi> it is that he has, as he ſpeaks ſomewhere? why this can be no leſs ſure then <hi>Bonaventures</hi> Son, or <hi>Bradwardines</hi> brother! <hi>What if the Magiſtrate ſhould require us not to reſiſt?</hi> If it were the Magiſtrate only required this, there were no doubt but we might reſiſt if he hurt or wrong us, as well as not obey his Laws if they be for our hurt. But it is Gods Commandment that we <hi>reſiſt not,</hi> and if he ſhall do us wrong or hurt we muſt bear it upon that account. It is but ſuffering <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his well</hi> and that is the reaſon why
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:39038:71"/>the Magiſtrate and Government it ſelf ſafe, when the Conſcience is yet at liberty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> avoid, if we can, any unjuſt, unreaſonab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> noxious, or unprofitable Law for the peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> You will ſay are we not bound to <hi>obey h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Laws,</hi> as well as not to reſiſt his authority<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I anſwer, there is this difference, we ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> no command from God that ſayes you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> obey this or that particular Law of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, or that you muſt indefinite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obey them all ſeeing ſome may be unjuſt ſome wicked, ſome vain; But there is a La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or command from God to be ſubject to the <hi>powers that are:</hi> whatſoever they are, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whatſoever they are, that is rightful power (for elſe the devil may come in) and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we muſt <hi>net reſiſt.</hi> I ſay moreover that to be ruled by the common good in civil affairs deſigned by his Miniſter, I take to be a Law of God of the ſame Nature as to be ſubject to the Magiſtrate, and to fear himſelf.</p>
               <p>After this, there is one paſſage more I will not paſs becauſe it looks lightly and is a conceſſion againſt himſelf, but does not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie if the word may nto offend) without a farther <hi>remove</hi> upon it. It is this. <hi>It is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed when a caſe of intollerable inconvenience
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:39038:71"/>happens that it being not the intention of a Prince to make his Subjects miſerable, he would not have made that Law if he could have foreſeen ſuch a miſcheif,</hi> and upon that account <hi>it cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be a Law, and looſes its obligation.</hi> I remember well that ſome indeed ſpeak thus, and when any take a Latitude in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to an individual caſe it will come to this, that ſuppoſing the Law-giver to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the circumſtances that this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular man is in, it is preſumed that he would conſent to the breach of his Law by that perſon, and upon this preſumption there may be many perhaps that abſolve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from ſeveral peices of obedience. That which may be ſaid for this is, that if the Law-giver is to be ſuppoſed not to <hi>intend to make his ſubjects miſerable</hi> by a Law; he is to be ſuppoſed not to intend to make <hi>any one</hi> miſerable for he cannot ſimply do the one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more then the other. <hi>Eadem eſt ratio u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius cujuſque &amp; Univerſorum.</hi> If ſuch a Law makes this or that particular man miſerable if he keep it, he will judge it to be the Law-givers intention, that he be diſpenſed with, that thoſe ſhould obſerve it who are made happy, or at leaſt not ſo diſtreſſed as he by it. There is ſomething I ſuppoſe of ſolidity
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:39038:72"/>in this, if we can find out for it a right bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. There is no particular perſon can ſay if the Law-giver had foreſeen this or the particular mans inconvenience he would no have made the Law, becauſe Laws in the nature are confinements and ſtreightnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to particular perſons for the good of the community. But this he muſt ſay, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> notwithſtanding the will of the Law-giver is indeed, that the generality ſhould keep the Law being for their good, yet it is to be underſtood with exception, to ſuch a ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or caſes, as his is. If he can give a reaſon now for this that will hold, it is well. The ſaying he made not his Law to make an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſimply miſerable is true, but in Relation to the publick he paſſed it though ſome ſhould be diſtreſſed by it: He cannot ſay therefore that he made not this Law to make him mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, but this he may ſay, that he made not this Law to make him or any man mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, but for the advantage of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, ſeeing for the benefit of the publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any one may be made to ſuffer dammage, whereas to make a Law that any might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it without advantage to the publick is unjuſt. There is neceſſity then to come here to my foundation and that is this. That the general end of every Law and Law-giver
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:39038:72"/>is (or ought to be and ſo is ſuppoſed to be) the publick advantage. VVhen any caſe then general or particular is ſuch that it is not for the publick benefit that a Law be obſerved, or that it is more for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good that it be not obſerved rather then obſerved, the Law-givers intention is to be ſuppoſed from the general end, that it ſhould not be obligatory to the Subject. His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is to oblige us to ſuch a thing for the publick good. But if ſuch a thing in ſuch a caſe be not for the publick good the obligation ceaſes being forſaken of his intention.</p>
               <p>There is much may be ſaid here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide what we inſiſt on before from the will of God.</p>
               <p>At the cloſe he preſents us with the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of two or three learned men for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all lawful commands of our ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. He might have taken the harmony of confeſſions, or moſt Diuines common pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and added as many more as he pleaſed of greater authority. He might find ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions too as ſtrict as any from ſome of our <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> Divines. But that which is to be anſwered to all is this, that we are to apprehend ſuch paſſages to be ſtill ſpoken
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:39038:73"/>upon ſuppoſition that the Laws or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the ſuperiours be good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Laws.</p>
               <p>They may put in the word <hi>lawfull</hi> only, but under it this muſt alſo be implyed. The honeſt and learned Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he ſpeaks of our duty to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, does judiciouſly uſe ſuch terms. <hi>VVe are bound to obſerve the good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Laws of the Nation whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ein we live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he and others ſpeaks thus it is plain that in the bottom of their minds they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, that if the Laws and commands of men be not <hi>good and wholeſome</hi> Laws or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, they are not accordingly bound to them, that is not in Conſcience bound, though the outward man be at the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſervice. And this I take it is that Light which does even almoſt Univerſally flow into the Souls of men, at the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of theſe matters, and as it is of Nature, it is from God. But who ſhall judge whether a Law be a good or whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Law or no? This I know may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain askt. It is a good and wholeſome Law I account when the thing commanded be for the common good. And I reply who ſhall judge whether that which be commanded be
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:39038:73"/>lawful or not? It will be a thing moſt foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to ſay, that he who hath paſſed the Law as good already muſt be judge, for then it might be no queſtion. You will ſay that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man muſt indeed be judge of that. I ſay then that if every man muſt judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the thing commanded him in a Law be according to Gods word or not, which is a matter of ſo much more difficulty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to his Soul, and where of the moſt of men are ſo much more indeed uncapable to judge with ſoundneſs, and yet every one muſt judge for himſelf according to his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in reference to his own practice, why ſhould any ſcruple to have the ſame ſaid in the queſtion whether it be for the common good, being what is eaſier done and a leſs matter? The ſum of the whole ſheets will come to this. The moſt both of Religious and Learned men are at a loſs (through their diſpute and jangling I ſuppoſe when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter elſe perhaps were more plain) in their conceptions about the obligation of human Laws. Two extreams we hear. The one that they bind not the Conſcience at all; the other, that they bind indefinitely, that is, all bind under pain of ſin. A middle path I have effered in reſolving the caſe. We ſee where
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:39038:74"/>it is the oppoſer does pinch. They will not allow the ſubject to be a reaſonable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in <hi>Politicals,</hi> when they cannot deny him to be ſo in <hi>Morals</hi> and things <hi>Religious.</hi> If they will allow us a judgement of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Civils,</hi> They muſt be ignorant, or conſider not, that the common good is the ſupream Law. That the ſupream muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-rule the ſubſervient. So long as any know not this, they are in darkneſs and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: But the Scintillations of this truth and Doctrine that I here have brought, are the feeds of Light and Liberty to the World. In which liberty the <hi>conſidering</hi> Chriſtian will <hi>ſtand faſt,</hi> and the tender will <hi>rejoyce in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:39038:74"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEfore <hi>I</hi> ſent theſe Sheets to the Preſs, at firſt I ſhewed them a Learned Dr. a perſon of note, as of ability, and I received his thoughts of them in the words which you find in the beginning. Being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from the Printer, <hi>I</hi> had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſhew them to another of the like eminency, and <hi>I</hi> received preſently a full Sheet from him upon the ſubject, I will make bold to ſet down thus much of it which follows.</p>
            <p>The Office <hi>(to wit, of the Magiſtrate)</hi> and exerciſe or adminiſtration being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, you truly ſay that he that is not bound in a particular caſe to obey, yet may be a Subject ſtill (which is the relation of one bound to ordinary obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience)
<pb facs="tcp:39038:75"/>and Rebellion which is the caſting off this ſubjection, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forbidden notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding a particular Law may be diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed.</p>
            <p>A Law made againſt God or the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Common-wealth is no Law <hi>in ſenſu uni voco</hi> but it is <hi>in ſenſu ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o vel analogico,</hi> and does not p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>perly bind the Subject.</p>
            <p>All men in their wits (that are maſters of ſuch diſcourſe) are agreed that <hi>judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium eſt vel publicum vel provatum. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licum eſt vel civile; Magiſtratus, per gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium exe quendum: Vel eccleſiaſtum, Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, per verbum &amp; clares exequendum: Et privatum diſcretionis eſt omnium.</hi> No Man ever obeyed without it, for <hi>authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas imperantis agnita,</hi> is the <hi>objectum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male obedientiae</hi> and anſwereth the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Quare obedis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Magiſtrate being by Office in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted
<pb facs="tcp:39038:75"/>with the <hi>bonum pubeicum</hi> the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is not called to try every one of his Laws whether they are ſuited to the <hi>bonum publicum</hi> or not, much leſs to be critical and buſie out of his place.</p>
            <p>But being not bound to be blind or or careleſs in a notorious caſe or ſuch of which he hath full and lawful cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, he may and muſt diſcern what command is againſt the common good.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
